<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Storeys</title><link>https://storeys.com/</link><description>Storeys</description><atom:link href="https://storeys.com/feeds/feed.rss" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:50:36 -0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://storeys.com/media-library/eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpbWFnZSI6Imh0dHBzOi8vYXNzZXRzLnJibC5tcy8zNDY2Mzc3Ni9vcmlnaW4uanBnIiwiZXhwaXJlc19hdCI6MTc5NjMxMzg3Nn0.-YvfgVityGCfOsIKwPOAR2cEzXMAqXf6UBb5TOiUGHs/image.jpg?width=210</url><link>https://storeys.com/</link><title>Storeys</title></image><item><title>Confident In Office, Europro JV Buys 7.8-Acre Yonge Corporate Centre From Cadillac Fairview</title><link>https://storeys.com/europro-acquires-yonge-corporate-centre/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/the-yonge-corporate-centre-at-4100-4150-yonge-street-in-toronto-europro.png?id=63758110&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>After first listing the Yonge Corporate Centre <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/elliot-medoff-3a436394_on-behalf-of-the-cadillac-fairview-corporation-activity-6973291566241124352-ODFX/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">three years ago</a>, pulling the listing, then re-listing the property this time <a href="https://storeys.com/cadillac-fairview-yonge-corporate-centre-listing/" rel="" target="_self">last year</a>, Toronto-based <a href="https://www.cadillacfairview.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Cadillac Fairview</a> has finally completed a sale of the sprawling office property.</p><p>In late January, Toronto-based commercial property management company <a href="https://www.europro.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Europro</a> announced that they had partnered with <a href="https://www.aristahomes.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Arista</a>, <a href="https://fieldgatecommercial.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Fieldgate Commercial</a>, and <a href="https://paradisedevelopments.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Paradise Commercial</a> to acquire the Yonge Corporate Centre, but did not disclose details about the transaction or ownership split.</p><p>One industry source said that the sale price was around $140 million at a cap rate of around 8.5%, but STOREYS could not independently verify the details. Reached for comment by STOREYS, a Europro representative declined to comment.</p><p>The Yonge Corporate Centre is located just north of the intersection of Yonge Street and York Mills Road, next to the Don Valley Golf Course. The 7.79-acre campus was constructed between 1985 and 1989 and consists of three six-storey office buildings located at 4100, 4110, and 4120 Yonge Street.</p><p>The campus is home to 649,808 sq. ft of Class A office space — split relatively evenly across the three buildings — plus 7,992 sq. ft of retail space in a standalone heritage building (4150 Yonge Street) that’s home French restaurant Auberge de Pommier, bringing the total amount of net rentable area to 657,800 sq. ft.</p><p>The property was listed by Peter Senst, Jaysen Smalley, and Kai Tai Li of CBRE alongside Ashley Martis, Elliot Medoff, and Alexandra Ivashenko of TD Cornerstone. Last year’s sales brochure noted that the Yonge Corporate Centre had an occupancy rate of 83%. Tenancies had a weighted average lease term of 3.6 years, with tenants including Ontario Lottery and Gaming, Dayforce, Wawanesa Insurance, Canadian Institute for Health Information, and BlueCat Networks.</p><p>The sales brochure also outlined the “significant residential redevelopment potential” of the site, including a development concept that would include four towers between 34 and 37 storeys, two towers between 24 and 27 storeys, and two buildings between 10 and 14 storeys. However, Europro has not indicated that it has any redevelopment plans and the company voiced a strong belief in the office market.</p><h4>A Return To Office?</h4><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="cb09b5635b3cd55aa08c6221d3a85cd9" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="0c666" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/the-yonge-corporate-centre-at-4100-4150-yonge-street-europro.jpg?id=63758074&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">The Yonge Corporate Centre at 4100-4150 Yonge Street. (Europro)</small></p><p>“We see clear indicators of strength returning to the office sector,” said Europro Vice President of Asset Management & Investments Jesse Nathanson in the <a href="https://www.europro.ca/media/europro-acquires-yonge-corporate-centre" target="_blank">press release</a>. “This acquisition aligns neatly with our strategy of owning and operating best-in-class office experiences in high-growth transit-oriented markets. […] This milestone reinforces our long-term commitment to the node. Expanding our presence here strengthens our ability to support the business community and positions our portfolio for sustained growth in one of Toronto’s most dynamic office markets.”</p><p>With the Yonge Corporate Centre acquisition, Europro now owns three significant assets along Yonge Street in the North Yonge corridor, with the other two being the 19-storey office tower at 5001 Yonge Street and the 24-storey Madison Centre at 4950 Yonge Street. The three assets total to over 1.5 million sq. ft.</p><p>Europro also said that it has a “strong conviction in the long-term vitality of the North Yonge market and the recovering office sector,” while Executive Vice President of Paradise Commercial Steven Weisz said he believes the office sector “is in the early innings of a strong comeback” and President & CEO of Arista Michael DeGasperis said that the partnership is “fully committed to enhancing this campus.”</p><p>According to a <a href="https://www.altusgroup.com/insights/canadian-office-market-update/" target="_blank">report</a> published by commercial real estate data and analytics firm Altus Group last week, the office availability rate in Toronto decreased to 16.7% in Q4 2025, a year-over-year decrease of 2.10%, and reflects a strong economic base and strong enforcement of return-to-office.</p><p>The absence of new construction — a trend present across most of the country — also contributed to the absorption of existing space, while the so-called “flight to quality” has also benefited Class AAA and A buildings across Canada.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:43:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/europro-acquires-yonge-corporate-centre/</guid><dc:creator>Howard Chai</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/png" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/the-yonge-corporate-centre-at-4100-4150-yonge-street-in-toronto-europro.png?id=63758110&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Preparing Your Home For Sale: The Complete Guide</title><link>https://storeys.com/seller-prepare-your-home-sale/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/unsplash.jpg?id=63704501&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p style="text-align: center;"><em>This article was written and submitted by <a href="https://www.clre.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Cameron Levitt</a>, a Toronto-based <a href="https://storeys.com/real-estate-agent-meaning-definition-real-estate/" target="_self">real estate agent</a> with RE/MAX Hallmark who writes about housing dynamics, market trends, and offers practical advice for buyers and sellers.</em></p><p>You wouldn't show up to a first date in dirty clothes, or walk into a job interview with your CV scribbled on a napkin. So why would you sell your biggest asset without the same level of care? </p><p>Selling requires preparation that costs time, money, and disrupts your daily life. Knowing what to prioritize is the difference between adding value and wasting effort. The best outcome balances maximizing sale price with what actually fits your life.</p><h3>Buyers Are Telling Themselves a Story</h3><p>When buyers view a home, they're building a narrative based on what they see. It's our job to shape that story. </p><p>A clean, well-maintained space tells buyers this home has been cared for and is ready for them. Clutter, visible damage, or neglected details tell a different story, shifting buyers out of imagination mode and into problem-solving mode.</p><p>Preparation removes these friction points so buyers stay focused on picturing themselves living there, rather than mentally cataloging repairs. That emotional connection is what drives offers. The goal is making sure buyers tell themselves the story you want them to hear.</p><h3>Be Realistic About Your Constraints</h3><p>Not every seller can do everything, and that's fine. Budget and time are always going to be constraints, so the goal is to allocate limited resources to the highest-impact areas. What makes sense for your specific property condition matters, too. You don't paint a house destined for demolition. </p><p>Understanding what will return value matters as much as what you can afford to spend. </p><p>The other crucial consideration is how much disruption your life can handle; turning your world upside-down while juggling work and family may not be worth the gain.</p><h3>The Basics</h3><p>Some things are non-negotiable, and cleanliness and decluttering are at the top of that list. Decluttering comes first. It makes rooms feel larger and helps buyers visualize themselves living there. When buyers can walk through without subconsciously cataloging what needs to be moved or stored, they remain focused on the space itself.</p><p>Practical decluttering steps include:</p><ul><li>Rent a storage locker for a month or two, if possible</li><li>Use this as an opportunity to purge old belongings</li><li>Improve flow by removing furniture that forces someone to walk around it or blocks sightlines to doors and windows</li><li>Create some negative space on countertops and bookshelves — aim for one or two intentional items</li><li>The garage should show that a car can comfortably fit</li><li>Edit personal items like photos and collections, but don't erase your personality</li><li>Keep closets to the current season of clothing — they should show storage space and not be overflowing</li></ul><p>Once the home is decluttered, it's easier to clean. A clean home shows the property has been cared for, while noticeable dirt immediately makes people feel uncomfortable. Cleaning is cheap, it's fast, and it sets the baseline for everything else.</p><p>Cleaning tips:</p><ul><li>Consider hiring professional cleaners for a deep clean — general or specialized (carpet, window, etc.)</li><li>Focus extra attention toward kitchen and bathrooms — grout, faucets, inside appliances</li><li>Eliminate odours from pets, cooking, and smoke (buyers notice these immediately)</li><li>Front entrance, door, and porch swept and clean</li><li>Baseboards, door frames, door handles and light switches (often overlooked)</li></ul><p>These two steps are low cost and have a very high impact. They're the foundation everything else builds on.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="97ab93a3be048becf0a1f60a3985e190" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="6ba85" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/pille-r-priske.jpg?id=63702358&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption..."><a href="https://unsplash.com/@pillepriske" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Pille R. Priske</a></small></p><h3>Know When DIY Makes Sense</h3><p>Now that we're moving into trade work, be honest about your skill level. Most people lack the time or ability to execute professional-quality work, and poor execution undermines the impression you're trying to create. Don’t try to do work that requires a licensed professional. Electrical, plumbing, and HVAC work can create liability and insurance issues. Trying to cut corners here can create legal and financial risk that isn't worth the savings.</p><p>This applies to design choices, too. Picking paint colours, light fixtures, or finishes requires an eye for what works in the space and what appeals to buyers. What feels modern or tasteful to you might read as dated or too specific to someone else. If you're uncertain about design decisions, get a second opinion from someone with experience in preparing homes for sale.</p><p>If you can't do professional-quality work, hire someone who can. The money spent on proper execution pays off in buyer confidence and final sale price.</p><h3>Paint Delivers the Best ROI</h3><p>Fresh paint is one of the best investments you can make when preparing a home for sale. It's inexpensive relative to the impact it creates, and it makes a space feel modern, clean, and move-in ready. The painting process should include repairing small damage like nail holes, chips, or dents in the walls. These minor repairs combined with fresh paint signal that the home has been well maintained. </p><p>If budget is tight, focus on high-impact areas where buyers spend the most time and form first impressions: the entrance, kitchen, main floor living areas, and master bedroom. These are the spaces where buyers linger and make decisions about whether they can see themselves living there. Less important rooms like basement spaces or back bedrooms can often be skipped if it's not possible to paint everything.</p><p>Stick to warm neutral colours that create a clean backdrop. The goal is to let buyers imagine their own style in the space, not compete with bold colour choices. White and off-white tones work well in most homes and appeal to the broadest range of buyers. </p><h3>Visual Consistency Creates Cohesion</h3><p>Even when individual spaces look good on their own, mismatched finishes or styles break the flow and create subtle discomfort for buyers. Consistency signals that the home is complete and intentional. Buyers register this intuitively, even if they can't articulate why something feels off.</p><p>Light fixtures are one of the highest-impact areas to address. Fixtures from different eras or styles throughout the home create disconnect. A brass chandelier in the dining room, brushed nickel in the kitchen, and oil-rubbed bronze in the bathrooms together tell buyers the updates happened piecemeal, over time. Unifying light fixtures to a consistent finish and style makes the home feel more cohesive.</p><p>Hardware throughout the house matters too. Door handles, door hinges, and kitchen cabinet hardware can be changed to create consistency in colour and finish. Having one colour throughout the house reinforces that sense of completeness and care.</p><p>If you're doing larger updates like a kitchen or bathroom renovation, make sure the design language fits the rest of the home. An ultra-modern kitchen in a traditional home or dated finishes in an otherwise contemporary space creates disconnect. The goal is for each room to feel like it belongs to the same house.</p><h3>Repairs: Small Fixes and Major Systems</h3><p>Remember, buyers are building a story about your home based on what they see. Unresolved repairs change that story from "well-maintained and ready" to "what else is wrong here?" Small repairs have outsized impact because buyers notice them immediately. Loose door handles, squeaky hinges, dripping taps, and sticky drawers are usually easy to fix and show the home has been cared for.</p><p>Major systems are different. Items like the roof, HVAC, and plumbing carry significant weight in buyer decisions. Leaving these unaddressed often costs more than fixing them. Buyers will either discount their offer by more than the actual repair cost or dismiss the property entirely. A new roof or furnace removes that uncertainty and prevents buyers from overestimating what needs to be done. If major repairs aren't feasible due to cost or timing, be transparent about the age and condition of major systems. Buyers handle known issues better than surprises discovered during inspection.</p><p>Finally, when making repairs, apply the consistency principle. If you're replacing flooring, hardware, or other visible elements, make sure the replacement matches or coordinates with existing materials.</p><h3>Curb Appeal Sets the Tone Before the Door Opens</h3><p>Curb appeal applies the same principles we've covered (cleanliness, repairs, paint, and consistency) to the front of your home. Focus on what's visible from the street and the front entrance.</p><p>Curb appeal checklist:</p><ul><li>Mow the lawn, edge walkways, and trim hedges</li><li>Weed flower beds and add fresh mulch</li><li>Power-wash walkways, driveway, and decks</li><li>Paint or clean the front door if needed</li><li>Paint or repair fence if visible from the street</li><li>Clear debris, toys, and clutter from the front yard</li><li>Clean gutters </li></ul><p>The goal is to make the approach feel welcoming and well-kept. First impressions matter, and the exterior is where that impression begins.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="f5677c0227d8eee544e1379dfa78de13" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="de74f" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/jon-sailer.jpg?id=63703236&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Jon Sailer</small></p><h3>Staging Completes the Picture</h3><p>Once repairs are done and the home is clean and decluttered, staging finishes the narrative. Good staging flows with the home's architecture and complements its visual language without stripping character.</p><p>Let's be honest: good staging is creating a showroom. No one actually lives like that. The furniture is perfectly scaled, there's no clutter, and everything is styled to highlight the home's best features. That's the point. We're creating an idealized version of life in the space that helps buyers imagine the potential. On the other hand, bad staging can undo all the work you've done to this point. Furniture that's too large, mismatched styles, or awkward layouts become distractions rather than assets.</p><p>If professional staging isn't in the budget, focus on the basics: furniture should be appropriately scaled, rooms should have clear purpose, styling should be inviting and broadly appealing. The goal is to make the home feel welcoming and complete.</p><h3>Final Thoughts</h3><p>Preparing a home for sale involves real costs: time, money, and disruption to your daily life. Understanding these realities should be taken into account at the early stages of considering a move, not after you've already committed. Planning the process at the beginning helps you make an informed decision about what it will actually take to sell your house.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:00:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/seller-prepare-your-home-sale/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/unsplash.jpg?id=63704501&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Grosvenor Acquires Full Ownership Of Victoria Broadmead Village Mall Valued At $95.5M</title><link>https://storeys.com/grosvenor-acquires-broadmead-village-mall/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/aerial-view-of-the-broadmead-village-shopping-centre-at-777-royal-oak-drive-in-victoria-grosvenor.jpg?id=63527526&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Grosvenor Property Canada, a subsidiary of UK giant <a href="https://www.grosvenor.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Grosvenor</a>, has acquired full ownership of the Broadmead Village Shopping Centre in one of British Columbia's first large retail transactions of 2026.</p><p>Broadmead Village is located at 777 Royal Oak Drive in Victoria, immediately east of the Patricia Bay Highway in the heart of the Saanich peninsula on Vancouver Island.</p><p>In an announcement this morning, Grosvenor said it has co-owned Broadmead Village with ADMNS — a subsidiary of the Manitoba Civil Service Superannuation Board (CSSB) pension plan — in equal partnership since 1997. Grosvenor has now bought out CSSB for $47.75 million in a deal that values Broadmead Village at $95.5 million.</p><p>Broadmead Village technically consists of two legal parcels: 777 Royal Oak Drive and 801 Royal Oak Drive, with the latter being home to Canadian Tire. Grosvenor has confirmed to STOREYS that the transaction involves only 777 Royal Oak Drive, which BC Assessment values at <a href="https://www.bcassessment.ca/Property/Info/QTAwMDBIUTM5RQ==" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">$85,854,000</a> in an assessment dated to July 1, 2025.</p><div class="rm-embed embed-media" style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" height="450" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d1321.9293665354141!2d-123.38217325!3d48.4976008!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x548f72180054acfb%3A0xff370f44c9421544!2s777%20Royal%20Oak%20Dr%2C%20Victoria%2C%20BC%20V8X%204V1!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sca!4v1769809264205!5m2!1sen!2sca" style="border:0;" width="600"></iframe></div><p>777 Royal Oak Drive was previously owned under ADMNS Broadmead Investment Corporation, and is now held under Broadmead GP Limited through Grosvenor Canada Limited.</p><p>It’s unclear who the owner of 801 Royal Oak Drive is, but Canadian Tire often owns their own real estate through CT REIT (TSX: CRT.UN). 801 Royal Oak Drive is valued at <a href="https://www.bcassessment.ca/Property/Info/QTAwMDBIUTM5Rg==" target="_blank">$11,152,000</a>.</p><p>The open-air neighbourhood shopping centre spans 128,018 sq. ft across 12.74 acres (excluding 801 Royal Oak Drive) and is anchored by Thrifty Foods, a supermarket chain owned by Sobeys. In 2012, Broadmead Village was extensively renovated and earned BOMA Bronze, Silver, and Gold accreditations.</p><p>In its announcement this morning, Grosvenor said Broadmead Village “has long been one of the best performing assets within Grosvenor’s Canadian property portfolio, exemplified by continued leasing momentum,” and that “its tenant mix is well-insulated from economic downturns with low historical turnover, vacancy, and strong performance.”</p><p>“Grosvenor’s first-class management of Broadmead Village parallels our experience with them as a long-term investment partner on other properties,” said Ian Cameron, Senior Portfolio Manager, Real Estate for Civil Service Superannuation Board (CSSB). “We are pleased with Broadmead Village’s performance over the decades, and notably, Grosvenor’s transformation of the property into one of Vancouver Island’s top performing grocery-anchored retail plazas.”</p><p>“We view this purchase as an outstanding opportunity to further our investment into Canada,” added Robert Duteau, SVP of Investment for Grosvenor Property Canada. “It highlights our strengths as an owner and manager, and follows our track record of developing and operating exceptional mixed use assets such as The Rise, Connaught and Grosvenor Ambleside.”</p><p>Notably, Duteau also suggested that redevelopment of Broadmead Village may be a possibility, saying that “acquiring grocery-anchored retail at scale with future redevelopment potential is an approach we are very focused on here in Canada.” Redevelopments of sprawling shopping centres have <a href="https://storeys.com/canada-vancouver-toronto-mall-redevelopments-housing-crisis/" rel="" target="_self">become a growing trend across Canada</a> as owners try to make better use of the land.</p><p>Grosvenor’s origins can be traced back to 1677 and the estate of Sir Thomas Grosvenor. Today, it remains owned by the Duke of Westminster, operating in various sectors on multiple continents.</p><p>In Canada, Grosvenor has been a presence for over 70 years now and it has multiple active real estate projects in its pipeline, including the <a href="https://storeys.com/grosvenor-mayfair-west-oakridge-transit-centre/" target="_self">Mayfair West</a> master-planned community in Vancouver and the <a href="https://storeys.com/grosvenor-burnaby-brentwood-block/" rel="" target="_self">Brentwood Block</a> master-planned community in Burnaby. The latter commenced construction last year. Grosvenor is also the owner of over 185 acres of Annacis Island and has approximately $2.8 billion in assets under management in Canada.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 21:47:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/grosvenor-acquires-broadmead-village-mall/</guid><dc:creator>Howard Chai</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/aerial-view-of-the-broadmead-village-shopping-centre-at-777-royal-oak-drive-in-victoria-grosvenor.jpg?id=63527526&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>How Canadian Developers Are Building For 2026 (And Beyond)</title><link>https://storeys.com/canada-developer-strategy-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/matias-santana-unsplash.jpg?id=63521627&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>It’s no secret that Canada’s homebuilding sector has weathered a few tough years. The country’s new condo sales in places like the Greater Toronto Hamilton Area (GTHA) have hit <a href="https://storeys.com/condo-completions-sales-urbanation-gtha/" target="_self"><u>lows</u></a> we haven’t seen in decades. The root causes – things like reduced immigration, high construction costs, elevated interest rates, and the collapse of investor demand – have created a perfect storm of volatility. An increasingly uncertain geopolitical climate (to say the least) doesn’t help. </p><p>So, it’s become common for Canadian developers to drop like dominoes, putting projects on hold or <a href="https://storeys.com/gtha-condo-cancellations-2024-urbanation/" target="_self"><u>cancelling them</u></a> altogether. Some, however, have strategically shifted focus to adjust for the changing times. This could mean moves like a pivot to purpose-built rentals, recapitalizing assets, increased cost consciousness, leveraging government incentives, and a reliance on vertical integration.<br/></p><p>The common denominator? These developers aren’t sitting on the sidelines. </p><h3>From Quick Flips to Forever Yields</h3><p><strong></strong>Purpose-built rentals continue their moment in the spotlight, as more developers have <a href="https://storeys.com/trend-purpose-built-rentals-2024/" target="_self"><u>shifted</u></a> from a reliance on condo pre-sales, to a focus on a more stable, recurring income in recent years. In 2025, Canada’s purpose-built rental starts hit an <a href="https://www.cmhc-schl.gc.ca/media-newsroom/news-releases/2025/canadas-vacancy-rate-rises-amid-historically-high-rental-construction" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>all-time high</u></a>, according to Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation (CMHC). Notable Canadian developers like Dream Unlimited Corp, Bosa Properties, and even the commercial real estate-focused RioCan have set their sights on the rental market as of late. </p><p>“Our pipeline is now split almost evenly between purpose-built rental and condo, and we continue to take a long-term view for both,” says Dan Cupa, SVP Residential at Vancouver’s <a href="https://bosaproperties.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Bosa Properties</u></a>. He says the current market structure requires an innovative shift. </p><p>“With rental now the dominant form of housing activity, competition is increasing, and that raises the bar,” says Cupa. “Success is measured by resident retention, operational performance, and the durability of the asset over time, which means designing rental communities with renters’ needs squarely in mind and continuing to provide exceptional property service.”</p><p>Pre-sales still matter, however. “For us, it isn’t a choice between pre-sales and rental yield,” says Cupa. “A healthy housing system needs both. Programs like BPI Equity [Bosa Properties’ rent-to-own program] reflect that reality by supporting renters who want a pathway into ownership, allowing us to build stronger relationships with our customers across different stages of their housing journey. Ultimately, success means delivering housing that works for how people live today and performs over the long term.”</p><p>While pre-sales are still important, the waning of the investor-driven condo market means a mass move away from the “investor shoebox” era that started around 2010. “Success today means designing homes for end-users with a focus on livability and enduring value,” says Cupa. </p><p><a href="https://danielshomes.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>The Daniels Corporation</u></a> is no stranger to purpose-built rentals, having built them in Toronto for over 30 years. While many developers may have been caught off guard by the conditions in 2024-2025, Daniels had the experience to shape how they plan capital in a way that supports housing through multiple market cycles, says Jake Cohen, President of the Daniels Corporation. </p><p>“While the current environment has reinforced the importance of that approach, our focus has long been on capital structures that prioritize resilience, diversification, and durability over short-term returns,” says Cohen. “Today, that means deepening our emphasis on purpose-built rental, including seniors’, student, affordable, and accessible housing, alongside low-rise development opportunities that respond to real demand and support more predictable outcomes.”</p><p>This allows Daniels to remain active while underwriting projects with longer horizons and greater financial durability, says Cohen. </p><h3>Selling Yesterday to Fund the Future</h3><p><strong></strong>While some developers may wait for conditions to improve or rates to drop, others are busy pruning their portfolios to finance the future. Some are selling off non-core assets in order to fund rental projects. </p><p>With properties across the country, <a href="https://dream.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Dream Unlimited Corp.</u></a> has been an industry benchmark for recapitalization. In the past 18 months, the developer has sold off non-core assets, like Colorado’s Arapahoe Basin Ski Resort, in order to crystallize a <a href="https://dream.ca/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Dream-A-Basin-FINAL.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>$110 million USD profit</u></a> to repay over $100 million in debt and bolster the liquidity needed to fund its massive recurring-income rental pipeline.</p><p>In August, Dream Impact Trust published a <a href="https://investors.dream.ca/wp-content/uploads/2025/08/MPCT-August-12-FINAL.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">general business update</a> on its liquidity, development, and strategic initiatives, revealing that it started the year with almost $350 million in land loans, and that it expects to reduce that total by $140 million. The developers claimed the loans have put a strain on their cash flow and liquidity. By the end of 2026, the Trust expects land loans to be reduced by over 60% compared to 2025 levels, primarily through strategic sales at Scarborough Junction and Quayside.</p><p>Similarly, RioCan REIT is in the midst of a massive $1.3–$1.4 billion capital recycling program. By offloading stakes in completed RioCan Living rental towers in Ottawa and Calgary to other REITs, the firm is generating the liquidity needed to deleverage its balance sheet while focusing on its core grocery-anchored residential pipeline.</p><h3>The Public-Private Playbook</h3><p>While government red tape has been blamed in part for delays in getting new homes built, strategic public-private partnerships are now fuelling the creation of new homes. “We’re seeing greater alignment from governments around the need to get housing built, particularly rental, even as the economics remain challenging,” says Cupa. “That doesn’t remove risk, but it does reinforce the importance of staying active rather than waiting on the sidelines.”</p><p>Government incentives like the removal of tax on new rental construction, CMHC’s Apartment Construction Loan Program, and the Housing Accelerator Fund have helped the homebuilding cause for developers who take advantage of them. </p><p>“The removal of taxes on purpose-built rentals has been hugely valuable,” says Jamie Cooper, President, Development and Income Properties at Dream Unlimited. “The federal government also provides attractive financing tools when you include affordability and sustainability in your buildings. When you commit to over 20% of the units being affordable, you get development charge waivers from the city. This helps to construct a large-scale project in downtown Toronto in a climate when few others are constructed.”<br/></p><p>Cooper points to Dream’s new project at <a href="https://storeys.com/dream-centrecourt-49-ontario-toronto/" target="_self"><u>49 Ontario Street</u></a> in downtown Toronto as a prime example. Built in partnership with CentreCourt Developments, it’s a mixed income, purpose-built rental with a significant affordable housing portion. Earlier this year, Dream Impact Trust, the current owner of the redevelopment site, secured up to $647.6 million in government-affiliated financing and obtained waivers for development charges from the City of Toronto for the 800,000 sq. ft project. The development will feature 1,226 multi-family units, with 22% designated as affordable housing.</p><p>However, the industry shift isn't about abandoning the private sector. Bryan Reid, President of Vancouver’s <a href="https://www.kindredconstruction.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Kindred Construction </a>notes that Kindred aims to stay "appropriately spread" across both sectors. “While publicly funded work may have increased impact on being mission driven as far as non-market, social or affordable housing, the private side serves as critical of a function to continue to increase our housing stock across all levels of affordability, and own forms of tenancy and ownership,” says Reid. </p><h3>Lean Design as a Financial Amenity</h3><p>Alan Nicholson, Principal and Founding Partner at construction management firm MAKE Projects, gives his clients a dose of tough love: “Your project isn’t stalled; it’s overdesigned for today’s economics,” he says – plain and simple. “We tell them to either simplify the building and reset the proforma to something financeable, or stop spending money trying to resurrect a version of the project the market can’t build anymore. This usually means a deep cut that the project team has been avoiding.”</p><p>When it’s time to cut costs, it’s out with the flashy, in with the practical. Nicholson says that British Columbia’s construction development industry "grew fat" during the prosperous years and that 2026 is a necessary lean period. This means reconsidering the nice-to-haves.</p><p>“For most of 20 years, proformas could absorb a lot: architectural gestures, complex systems, overly bespoke detailing, and also policy enhancements around sustainability and accessibility, and increasing code requirements,” says Nicholson. “The fundamental underpinnings of rental rates, population growth, and amazingly consistent real estate value growth maintained the profitability of real estate investment. In 2024 and 2025, the fundamentals changed, and the ability to absorb disappeared.” </p><p>However, Nicholson highlights that policy doesn't retract quickly, if ever, calling construction material and labour pricing “notoriously sticky.” So, he advises clients to re-evaluate their design decisions; what used to be a necessary flashy extra may no longer be necessary (bye bye, theatre room). </p><p>Being fiscally responsible also means environmental considerations to avoid future carbon tax and operating costs. “We take a pragmatic approach to balancing carbon performance with financial discipline,” Cohen says of Daniels. “Our goal is to push low-carbon performance as far as possible while remaining responsible to our development partners and the long-term viability of each project.”</p><p>He says efficiency is key. “By focusing on building performance and reducing energy demand through better envelopes and smarter systems, we can remove inefficiencies elsewhere,” he says. “That creates room in the budget to invest in sustainability measures where the benefits are realized over time through lower operating costs and reduced risk.” </p><p>Daniels recently completed the first phase of Brampton’s MPV2 development, which utilizes geo-exchange and solar technology to lower long-term operating costs. </p><h3>Taking Control: In-House Infrastructure</h3><p><strong></strong>Vertical integration is often the best defence. In a climate of sky-high construction costs and labour shortages, it helps to have an in-house construction team. Those with an in-house construction arm aren't optimizing for a single phase of a project, rather, optimizing for the full lifecycle of buildings across their portfolio. Cupa says that<strong> </strong>this type of vertical integration gives Bosa Properties clarity and control. </p><p>“Because our construction team is part of the same organization, we’re able to make decisions earlier, design more efficiently, and adjust quickly when conditions change,” says Cupa. “That doesn’t mean we’re immune to cost pressures – no one is – but it does mean fewer surprises to project budgets or schedules. We can design with quality in mind, sequence work more strategically, and keep skilled trades consistently employed rather than cycling on and off projects. From a fiscal responsibility standpoint, that long-term lens matters.”</p><p>To further ensure execution certainty, Dream’s partnership with CentreCourt on 49 Ontario brings in a partner specifically known for self-performing construction at unmatched speed. This insulates the project from the scheduling delays that have notoriously plagued the GTHA.</p><p>Meanwhile, Daniels has recently brought strategic design and engineering oversight in-house and evolved its leadership structure to focus on construction as a service. Recently, it appointed its first Chief Construction Officer, Gokul Pisharoty. The expansion of their development management and construction management services will allow Daniels to build with and for others. </p><p>“This enables us to apply our expertise in complex, mixed-income and low-carbon projects while generating stable, fee-based revenue and supporting partners across the public, institutional, and non-profit sectors,” explains Cohen. “Together, these strategies reflect a disciplined approach to capital deployment; one that sustains housing supply, and aligns long-term financial stability with community impact, regardless of market cycles.”</p><h3>The Path Forward: Innovation Through Repetition</h3><p><strong></strong>Scaling building efficiencies for today's climate requires efficient repetition. Reid points to the Vienna House project in East Vancouver, which relies on prefab “clip-on” technology and mass timber, as a proving ground for industrialized construction.</p><p>“Innovation within the construction space takes repetition,” says Reid. "It will start slow, until it’s very quick.” He says that as these methods scale, the ability to do "more with less on-site labour" will eventually offset rising material costs.</p><p>Strategically navigating 2026 ultimately comes down to collaboration and speed. As Reid puts it, builders must invest in their clients' efforts early to find a path to viability. “Being efficient with schedules to avoid delays – as debt remains expensive and delays are very costly – is paramount,” he says.</p><p>Nicholson echoes the sentiment. “We always advocate for a tightly controlled project with good leadership, which will allow trimming of the budgets with tighter contingencies,” he says. “We cannot overstate the importance of this for cost control.”</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 19:26:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/canada-developer-strategy-2026/</guid><dc:creator>Erin Nicole Davis</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/matias-santana-unsplash.jpg?id=63521627&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Hullmark Buys Spadina Road Retail Property For $21.7M</title><link>https://storeys.com/hullmark-buys-spadina-retail-property/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/hullmark.jpg?id=63519781&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Toronto-based developer <a href="https://www.hullmark.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Hullmark</a> recently acquired the retail complex at 446 Spadina Road in the Forest Hill Village neighbourhood, continuing to add to its portfolio of assets.</p><p>The property consists of two levels of retail space with one floor of office space above, and the mixed-use building is fully leased, with tenants including Forest Hill Spa, Forest Hill Pets, a Starbucks, and others.</p><p>The sale price was $21,750,000, translating to a rate of $802 per square foot. The sale was brokered by Ming Zee and Nick Nankissoor of CB Metropolitan Commercial.</p><p><em>STOREYS</em> reached out to Hullmark last week and has not received a response, but the company previously <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7413951959822696449/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">announced</a> the acquisition on social media.</p><p>“Located in the heart of Toronto’s Forest Hill Village neighbourhood, the Property is surrounded by established residential communities, strong transit infrastructure, and several notable schools,” said Hullmark. “446 Spadina Road represents a strategic addition to Hullmark’s growing portfolio, reinforcing our commitment to investing in high-quality urban properties in Toronto’s most established neighbourhoods.”</p><p>It’s unclear if there are redevelopment plans, but no application has been submitted, according to City of Toronto records.</p><p>About a year ago, however, Toronto City Council approved a development proposal for 1-19 Thelma Avenue, located around the corner, where Cranson Capital and Dealcore Properties are planning a six-storey boutique luxury condo building. Cranson Capital’s <a href="https://www.cransoncapital.com/thelma-avenue" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">website</a> states that marketing and sales were expected to launch in June 2025, but it’s unclear if that occurred.</p><p>Year-end data for 2025 is just starting to come out, but investment in commercial real estate was down last year, according to data and analytics firm Altus Group.</p><p>“In 2025, Canada’s commercial real estate investment activity experienced a modest contraction, with total dollar volume falling to approximately $51 billion,” said Altus Group in a <a href="https://www.altusgroup.com/insights/canadian-cre-investment-trends/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">report</a> published last week. “This represented an 8% year-over-year decrease, reflecting a pronounced pullback as investors remained hesitant to deploy capital amidst sustained macroeconomic volatility.”</p><p>Altus Group says 2025 showed that investors have a preference for stable, lower-risk assets, with retail assets being one such type. There are also some positives as we head deeper into the new year.</p><p>“However, as the market moved toward 2026 with a more definitive outlook on interest rate stabilization, projections suggested that institutional capital would likely begin to migrate from the sidelines toward defensive, high-quality assets.” </p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 17:32:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/hullmark-buys-spadina-retail-property/</guid><dc:creator>Howard Chai</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/hullmark.jpg?id=63519781&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Bank Of Canada Holds Interest Rate Steady In First 2026 Announcement</title><link>https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-january-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/bank-of-canada-x.jpg?id=53848799&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C0%2C0%2C0"/><br/><br/><p>On Wednesday, the Bank of Canada held its policy rate at 2.25%, following a series of cuts in 2025 that brought the benchmark overnight rate to its current level. </p><p>Leading up to the announcement, many major Canadian banks — including <a href="https://www.rbc.com/en/economics/wp-content/uploads/sites/23/2025/12/MFUDec25.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">RBC</a>, <a href="https://economics.td.com/ca-forecast-tables" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">TD</a>, and <a href="https://economics.cibccm.com/cds?id=5e81ef9f-a852-474b-ab95-f3bd6aeb3925&flag=E" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">CIBC</a> — came into 2026 expecting the Bank to maintain a steady policy stance. </p><p>Alongside the announcement came the Bank's <em>Monetary Policy Report, </em>in which the Bank said the economic outlook is largely unchanged since fall — but remains vulnerable to unpredictable US trade policies and geopolitical risks.</p><p>The report notes the US economy is outperforming expectations, driven by AI investment and steady consumer spending, though tariffs are keeping inflation elevated. Europe is growing on strong service-sector activity and fiscal support, while China’s GDP is slowing as weaker domestic demand offsets export gains. </p><p>Overall, global growth is projected to average about 3%.</p><p>At home, growth is modest — slowed by US trade restrictions and broader uncertainty. After a strong Q3, GDP likely stalled in Q4. </p><p>The report explains exports are constrained, domestic demand is picking up, and employment is rising, though the unemployment rate remains 6.8% with few businesses planning new hires. The Bank projects 1.1% growth in 2026 and 1.5% in 2027, with trade uncertainty around the Canada-US-Mexico agreement still a risk.</p><p>Inflation ticked up to 2.4% in December due to last year’s GST/HST holiday, but core measures are easing — down from 3% in October to about 2½%. Overall, 2025 inflation averaged 2.1%, and the Bank expects it to stay near 2% as trade pressures are offset by excess supply.</p><p>Monetary policy remains focused on keeping inflation on target while supporting the economy through adjustment. The current policy rate is considered appropriate, but the Bank says risks are being monitored closely, with action poised to maintain price stability.</p><p><span></span>The next interest rate decision is scheduled for Wednesday, March 18. A full 2026 schedule can be found <a href="https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-announcements-2026/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 14:57:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-january-2026/</guid><category>Bank of canada</category><category>Interest rates</category><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/bank-of-canada-x.jpg?id=53848799&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Soft Curves, Strong Vision: Don't Miss This Trinity Bellwoods Home</title><link>https://storeys.com/44-foxley-street-for-sale/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/44-foxley-street-realtor-ca.png?id=63351713&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>In a city that’s no stranger to architectural ambition, <a href="https://www.realtor.ca/real-estate/29289042/44-foxley-street-toronto-trinity-bellwoods-trinity-bellwoods" target="_blank">44 Foxley Street</a> still manages to stand apart.</p><p>Tucked into the Trinity Bellwoods neighbourhood, the residence is a sculptural rethink of what contemporary urban living can look like.</p><p>From the street, the home reads as fluid and deliberate, with soft curves and signature arches that immediately set it apart from the city’s more angular stock. </p><div class="rm-embed embed-media" style="text-align: center;"><iframe allowfullscreen="" height="450" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2887.026355563362!2d-79.42201!3d43.647619999999996!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x882b35943579e5f7%3A0x133eb7095cdd85fe!2s44%20Foxley%20St%2C%20Toronto%2C%20ON%20M6J%201P9!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sca!4v1769537528793!5m2!1sen!2sca" style="border:0;" width="600"></iframe></div><p>Step inside, and that language continues uninterrupted, carrying through each level as a cohesive narrative rather than a collection of fragmented design moments. It’s a space that feels considered from every angle — not just styled, but composed.</p><p><strong>SPECS</strong></p><ul><li><strong>Address</strong>: 44 Foxley Street, Toronto</li><li><strong>Bedrooms</strong>: 5+2</li><li><strong>Bathrooms</strong>: 8</li><li><strong>Listed At</strong>: $3,895,000</li><li><strong>Listed By</strong>: Stephanie Anne Newlands, Royal LePage Real Estate Services</li></ul><p>The main level is anchored by a bespoke Scavolini kitchen, paired with Gaggenau appliances and seamlessly connected to expansive living and dining areas. </p><p>The result is a floor that flows effortlessly, balancing visual drama with everyday functionality and setting a high bar for spatial elegance in a dense urban context.</p><p>Across three levels, the home unfolds with four bedrooms and six bathrooms, each designed to complement the overarching architectural vision. The third-floor primary retreat stands out as a statement within a statement, featuring custom millwork, a spa-like ensuite, and access to a private terrace that feels worlds away from the bustle below. </p><p>Throughout the home, comfort is carefully calibrated, with multiple air conditioning systems ensuring each level maintains its own ideal climate.</p><p><em>______________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________</em></p><p style="text-align: center;"><strong><em>Our Favourite Thing</em></strong></p><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Beyond the main home, there’s the laneway house — a fully realized extension rather than an afterthought. Mirroring the curved forms and meticulous craftsmanship of the main residence, the two-storey space offers remarkable flexibility, whether as guest accommodations, a private studio, or a work-from-home escape that’s truly separate from the main house.</em></p><p><em><em>______________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________</em></em></p><p>More than a single-family home, 44 Foxley Street reads as a modern interpretation of Toronto’s evolving urban fabric — one that prioritizes architectural continuity, elevated living, and thoughtful density.</p><p> In a neighbourhood defined by creativity and character, it manages to push the conversation forward while still feeling perfectly at home.</p><h3>WELCOME TO 44 FOXLEY STREET</h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="e25b4a4e59899f6e6df50f01b6e79774" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="0b3cd" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351539&width=980"/><h3>LIVING, KITCHEN, AND DINING</h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="4f935605f4334cecb6bed78b95ddf0de" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="3138e" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351533&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="e8b205f48204f61a112f5fad82f94f90" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="27f98" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351537&width=980"/><h3>BEDS AND BATHS</h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="3e18d185f1d5d6b4ddb6127013bec507" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="149f1" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351529&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="853223a136ae84923fe4f49e1c4f632a" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="a66e0" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351535&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="9f073a27b8da13640d17f2fb9cc1ec47" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="bc6e3" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351534&width=980"/><h3>BACKYARD</h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="03e394b0bf9a10eca23af27cb1863cde" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="daa00" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351543&width=980"/><h3>LANEWAY HOME</h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="7ec1a56dff5d3e9a33c496b5f03b4799" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="5349b" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351542&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="d7359f56c1b25c16541555f03c019ce6" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="29183" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351538&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="19413083123f1450fc4128756b23d4c8" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="a4724" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351536&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="a8d78163bd988df63e18cf5be48349b2" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="5e030" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=63351544&width=980"/><p class=""><em>Images via <a href="https://www.realtor.ca/real-estate/29289042/44-foxley-street-toronto-trinity-bellwoods-trinity-bellwoods" target="_blank">realtor.ca</a>.</em></p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:21:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/44-foxley-street-for-sale/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/png" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/44-foxley-street-realtor-ca.png?id=63351713&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Vancouver General Hospital Unveils 10-Phase Campus Redevelopment Plan</title><link>https://storeys.com/vancouver-general-hospital-redevelopment-application/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=63339928&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Last week, the City of Vancouver published a rezoning application that may have the biggest impact of any planned development project in the city: a 10-phase long-term redevelopment of the 35-acre Vancouver General Hospital (VGH) campus.</p><p>In a press release, <a href="https://www.vch.ca/en/about-us/our-vision/strategic-priorities/development-projects/vancouver-general-hospital-campus" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Vancouver Coast Health</a> (VCH) said the rezoning application “will enable the hospital campus to grow sustainability and continue to meet the evolving needs of patients, clients, staff, medical staff, and partners from across the province” and called it “an important first step in establishing a long-term planning framework for how the hospital campus could evolve to meet growing health-care demands and care delivery needs.”</p><p>The envisioned redevelopment serves as a framework for the revitalization of the campus, which is expected to take at at least 30 years and to be constructed across 10 carefully coordinated phases that will ensure VGH remains fully operational throughout. The campus rezoning application is akin to what other municipalities refer to as a master plan rezoning application, with construction phases to be guided by future development applications. Vancouver Coast Health would also need to secure approval and funding from the Province first.</p><p>Vancouver Coast Health is partnering with <a href="https://kasian.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Kasian Architecture and Interior Design</a> on the project and their <a href="https://www.shapeyourcity.ca/855-w-12-ave" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">rezoning application</a> goes into great detail about the state of VGH and “an urgent public health crisis that requires an immediate response.”</p><p>According to VCH, bed shortages “create daily operational challenges,” delaying inpatient admissions from the Emergency Department, and demand is projected to surge over the next decade as the population of those aged 70+ is expected to grow 47% by 2035. The hospital's Emergency Department was built in the mid-70s, and 80% of inpatient beds are located in facilities built between 1953 and 1989. The local population — particularly in the <a href="https://storeys.com/vancouver-broadway-plan-review-2024/" rel="" target="_self">Broadway Plan corridor</a>, where VGH is located — is also expected to grow, and overall demand for healthcare is expected to follow.</p><p><em><br/></em></p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="d7ed11ffceaf816d07ef3808fda89652" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="92d03" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/an-overview-of-the-vancouver-general-hospital-campus-and-the-ages-of-the-buildings-kasian-architecture-vancouver-coastal-heal.jpg?id=63339940&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">An overview of the Vancouver General Hospital campus and the ages of the buildings. (Kasian Architecture, Vancouver Coastal Health)</small></p><p>The VGH campus was rezoned in 2002, but “this framework no longer reflects the realities of redeveloping a large, land-locked hospital precinct into a modern, resilient, and sustainable health campus that evolves and expands with the community it serves,” the new application states, citing density constraints, height restrictions, and site coverage limitations as contributing factors.</p><p>“Given the limited land availability, future expansion must occur vertically, as horizontal sprawl is not feasible,” the application states. “As a result, the proposed new buildings will be taller and more space-efficient, contributing to an overall increase in campus density. […] A key principle of the plan is that new patient care facilities must be constructed and operational before older clinical buildings can be vacated and decommissioned.”</p><p>Over 300,000 sq. m — 3.2 million sq. ft — of modernized healthcare space in buildings up to 24 storeys is being proposed, with a maximum site density of approximately 5.0 FSR. (The VGH campus is currently around 2.43 FSR.) The rezoning application also proposes a suite of changes to things such as the zoning boundary, site coverage, open space requirements, heritage conservation requirements, and more.</p><p>The rezoning application provides a broad outline of all 10 phases, with the first phase to be focused on removal of non-clinicial buildings such as the Laundry Building, Research Pavilion, Heather Pavilion, Tzu Chi Building, and Doctors’ Residence. The application states that these buildings “can be temporarily relocated off-site without disrupting patient services.”</p><p><em><br/></em></p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="eb6a87ca213ecc62cb6ac19d2b116628" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="ebee6" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/the-existing-vgh-campus-and-phase-one-plan-kasian-architecture-vancouver-coastal-health.jpg?id=63339943&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">The existing VGH campus and Phase One plan. (Kasian Architecture, Vancouver Coastal Health)</small></p> <p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="42389f742d5bb1c1bf64bf55bb6d05dd" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="596ac" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/the-layout-of-the-new-vgh-campus-after-the-10-phase-redevelopment-kasian-architecture-vancouver-coastal-health.jpg?id=63339950&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">The layout of the new VGH campus after the 10-phase redevelopment. (Kasian Architecture, Vancouver Coastal Health)</small></p> <p>Latter phases will then see the clinical buildings, such as the Leon Blackmore Pavilion and the Jim Pattison Pavilion, replaced — after new facilities are operational. Vancouver Coastal Health says there is currently a parking shortfall and that multi-level underground parkades will be included in three of the large new buildings to be constructed. The exact numbers have yet to be finalized, but the application states that 4,985 vehicle parking stalls would result in a surplus that ensures long-term adequacy. The number for bicycle parking is 925, not including short-term parking.</p><p>Each phase is also expected to include enhancements to the public realm that will “strengthen the identity of the campus, support intuitive wayfinding, and provide a meaningful connection to nature for all who use the site.” The rezoning application also states that the redevelopment plan “ensures that a baseline amount of open space is preserved permanently throughout all phases of development.”</p><p>In addition to the campus-wide rezoning application, VCH and Kasian have also submitted a rezoning text amendment application that would enable the first two phases. This application would be processed concurrently with the campus-wide rezoning and allows VCH to demolish the Laundry Building and Research Pavilion along West 10th Avenue, then construct a new 11-storey building (Building 1 in the image above) that would serve as an expansion of the Emergency Department currently located in the Jim Pattison Pavilion.</p><p>The City of Vancouver is holding the Q&A period for the campus-wide rezoning from Wednesday, February 11 to Tuesday, February 24, and an in-person information session has been scheduled for Wednesday, February 18 from 4:30 pm to 7:30 pm in the Paetzold Auditorium within the Jim Pattison Pavilion. </p><p>The application will then go to the Urban Design Panel on Wednesday, March 25. </p><p>Some enabling policy changes are expected to be considered by Council in Summer 2026, with consideration of the campus-wide rezoning to follow.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:58:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/vancouver-general-hospital-redevelopment-application/</guid><dc:creator>Howard Chai</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=63339928&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Vacancy Rises As Rent Growth Cools Across Canada: Report</title><link>https://storeys.com/canada-rent-yardi-january-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/remi-carreiro-unsplash.png?id=63342341&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C30%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>After several years of tight conditions, Canada’s purpose-built rental market is beginning to show signs of normalization.</p><p>That’s the picture painted by Yardi’s latest <a href="https://info.yardi.com/multifamily-market-reports-for-canada/" target="_blank">Canadian National Multifamily Report</a>, which recaps Q4 2025 and shows a market that remains broadly resilient — but increasingly balanced — as new supply comes online, vacancy rises, and rent growth cools across major metros.</p><p>That shift is being driven in part by new supply, with Canada’s largest metros adding more than 94,600 rental units through November 2025, per CMHC and Common Sense Economics. It’s one of the strongest stretches of purpose-built rental delivery in years, and the impact is now showing up in pricing and availability. </p><p>While several large markets — including Toronto, Montreal, Ottawa–Gatineau, and Calgary — recorded year-over-year declines in deliveries, Vancouver and Edmonton saw significant increases, underscoring how uneven the supply story remains across the country.</p><p>National new-lease rent growth slowed to just 0.7% in Q4 2025, down sharply from 2.4% in Q3 and 6.4% a year earlier. Several Ontario markets tipped into negative territory, including Kitchener–Cambridge–Waterloo (-2.7%), Toronto (-1.0%), and Hamilton (-0.2%), reflecting softer demand tied to outmigration, a pullback in non-permanent residents, and growing competition from condominium units being rented after failing to sell.</p><p>In-place rents are also losing momentum. The national average increased just $9 in Q4 to $1,746 — the smallest quarterly increase in more than four years — bringing annual growth down to 3.2%. Halifax, Montreal, and Ottawa–Gatineau posted the strongest year-over-year gains, while Calgary was the only major market to record a decline.</p><p>Vacancy continues to climb. Canada’s national apartment vacancy rate rose to 4.5% in Q4 2025, the highest level since Yardi began tracking in 2020. Vacancy rates were highest in Calgary, Edmonton, Montreal, Saskatoon, and Hamilton, and increased year-over-year in most major CMAs, including Toronto and Vancouver. Population growth has slowed sharply, with Statistics Canada estimating just 81,000 net new residents in 2025, the smallest year-over-year increase in decades, driven in part by reduced targets for non-permanent residents and record-high outflows as temporary permits expire.</p><p>Despite the softening, Yardi stresses that the market isn’t breaking. Housing supply remains structurally constrained, meaning occupancy should hold up outside of specific segments such as bachelor units. Operating costs, however, remain elevated, averaging $8,004 per unit annually in 2025, with the highest expenses recorded in Ontario and Alberta.</p><p>“Canada’s rental market is entering a new chapter,” said Peter Altobelli, Vice President and General Manager of Yardi Canada. “We haven’t seen this level of new purpose-built rental supply in a long time, and it’s already shifting market conditions.”</p><p>The takeaway heading into 2026 is a familiar one: fundamentals are still intact, but the balance of power is shifting. And for the first time in years, renters in several major markets are seeing some breathing room.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:53:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/canada-rent-yardi-january-2026/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/png" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/remi-carreiro-unsplash.png?id=63342341&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Year-Ahead Outlook: Industry Insiders On What To Expect In 2026</title><link>https://storeys.com/2026-market-outlook-canada/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/shivendu-shukla.jpg?id=63131865&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>If 2025 was about waiting things out, 2026 is about finding out what still works. </p><p>Experts across development, construction, investment, and beyond say the real estate industry appears to be moving from pause to pressure-testing.</p><p>That shift is unfolding amid global volatility, evolving trade dynamics, and local conditions that continue to influence how capital is deployed and projects move forward. To get our bearings and provide context for the months ahead, the perspectives below reflect what industry leaders are seeing — and saying — as the year gets underway.</p><h3>A Volatile Foundation</h3><p>Ben Taddei, Partner and Chief Operating Officer at <a href="https://conwest.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>ConWest Developments</u></a>, says volatility is his baseline assumption heading into 2026.</p><p>“High-level, I’m expecting a lot of volatility in the world. That’s going to materialize into uncertainty, which is going to cause people to pause.” Focusing on Vancouver specifically, Taddei points to a number of local pressures that he expects will continue to weigh on the market.</p><p>“The implications on Vancouver real estate are [that volatility], plus the micro factors." Factors, he explains, that will continue to be challenged throughout the year ahead, due to a lack of immigration — both nationwide and in British Columbia — alongside tight monetary policy, economic uncertainty related to Indigenous land rights, and a cost-of-delivery problem. </p><p>"All that means: another challenging year for real estate in Vancouver,” he says. Still, Taddei notes certain segments are showing resilience.</p><p>"What I'm seeing is a lot of activity in the large-format industrial sector. We’re seeing multiple offers on large buildings; that’s going to put upward pressure, shortly, on lease rates for those buildings. That’s an early indicator we might be approaching the bottom in that market. But residential, primarily, is going to be challenging.”</p><p>The slowdown Taddei describes has been especially visible for builders. Bryan Reid, President of <a href="https://www.kindredconstruction.com/about/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Kindred Construction Ltd.</u></a>, says the stalling seen last year has carried forward into 2026.</p><p>“[In 2026, the] market [is] set for further disruption due to fiscal constraints faced by various levels of government," Reid says. </p><p>"While housing and infrastructure development is critically needed, the financial realities faced by projects that don't make sense (on the private side), and ballooning debt (on the public side) will likely see project starts pull back further in the near term. The focus on all projects will be cost-consciousness in order to make them as viable as possible, with other goals (green initiatives, innovation, etc.) that come with costs regrettably, likely, taking a back seat.”</p><h3>The Reset: Capital, Costs, and Underwriting</h3><p>From a planning and advisory standpoint, Kevin Hussey, President of Development & Construction at <a href="https://pennyfarthinghomes.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Pennyfarthing Homes</u></a>, says sluggish presales have already forced a strategic reset.</p><p>“With presales slowing, developers have pivoted to rental at scale. In a low-immigration environment, absorption — not headline rent — has becomes one of the key variables. Substantial new supply will hit the market in 2026, and we expect that underwriting will shift from '<em><em>what are asking rents?'</em></em>' to '<em><em>what are the effective rents after incentives, and how quickly can we lease up?',"</em></em> Hussey says. "Near term, we expect more inducements, longer stabilization, and a tighter 2026–27 pro-forma as expectations reset ahead of healthier fundamentals in the next cycle.”</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="56867caffbcbb0fe9797612aabf646ce" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="75b75" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/pennyfarthing-s-the-capstone-langley-pennyfarthinghomes-ca.png?id=63131942&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Pennyfarthing's The Capstone, Langley (pennyfarthinghomes.ca)</small> </p><p>Meanwhile, David Basche, President of <a href="https://astriaproperties.com/" target="_blank"><u>Astria Properties</u></a>, notes that operating across British Columbia and Alberta has provided insight into how regional dynamics are diverging — particularly when it comes to capital deployment.</p><p>“The political uncertainty locally, coupled with [difficulty in] our regulatory environment from an entitlement perspective, has been dampening the market a lot," he says. "Of course, the Cowichan land claim issue is a looming cloud over British Columbia. And one of the biggest things we're seeing is that the big capital groups who are looking to invest in BC are treading very cautiously right now. That's obviously a big problem for our market, because we want to expand the industrial property base." </p><p>Basche explains that this carries over into other asset classes, too. "There are a lot of groups out here that raise capital through [those big capital partners], but these groups have, historically, also been active in acquiring, so that uncertainty affects not just us, from a development perspective, but also the capital partners. And then, more importantly, the businesses that are looking to expand in Vancouver." He notes, however, that these groups have shown strong leasing activity through Q4 and early 2025, signalling the start of normalization — but uncertainty remains with shifting activity south of the border.</p><p>"[Tariff escalations make] business really unpredictable," Basche says. "[Today,] most industrial businesses are acutely aware of what tariffs mean to their company and how they work. They know they're in place. Of course, the bigger issues is: are they changing? How fast are they changing? So hence why we're seeing a bit of a mixed decision making." He explains that while large companies have capacity for deep insight into tariff action, smaller organizations can struggle to keep up with quick and constant changes. </p><p>Conversely, Basche points to other market segments — particularly retail development — as being on the up as a post-COVID world continues to bloom. "We've seen great demand in retail for new developments," he says. "Those locations are incredibly hard to find, but if you have a location where you can build a grocery store with a drug anchor, a bank, and quick-serve restaurants, the capital is there. The tenants are there. The desire to execute from all other parties involved is there. It's been a really good business to be in, and we foresee that continuing to be really strong throughout 2026.”</p><p>In other words, things are undeniably moving again. But not everywhere, and not for everyone. </p><h3>Selective Momentum</h3><p>“After a couple of years dominated by rates and uncertainty, 2026 should be a year of cautious momentum," says Damon Conrad, Vice President & Head of Commercial, <a href="https://www.remax.ca/" target="_blank">REMAX Canada</a>. "Financing is becoming more workable bringing buyers and sellers back to the table, but it will be selective and quality led, with the best buildings and locations outperforming."</p><p>"Industrial is normalizing after an extraordinary run, retail has been more resilient than many expected, and office remains a tale of two markets, between space that fits how people work today, and space that needs a new plan," Conrad continues. "Activity should improve, but only where fundamentals and pricing align.”</p><p>Against that backdrop, there are also signs that the broader market may be nearing an inflection point. Diego Mandelbaum, Chief Development Officer at <a href="https://www.corix.com/" target="_blank"><u>Corix</u></a>, offers a cautiously optimistic view.</p><p>“In a world where uncertainty has become the only certainty, I expect 2026 to mark the beginning of a soft recovery — or at the very least, the end of the fall," Mandelbaum says. "I anticipate the wheat being separated from the chaff, with those hyper-focused on value and affordability beginning to bounce back, while those who aren’t continue to tread water. Even this fickle market is showing glimmers of hope that discipline may be rewarded again.”</p><p>At the residential level, early-year conditions remain subdued. Maryrose Coleman of <a href="https://sothebysrealty.ca/en/halloran-and-associates/" target="_blank"><u>Halloran & Associates, Sotheby’s International Realty Canada</u></a>, points to broader global conditions and seasonal timing.</p><p>“With the continued geopolitical turmoil in the world, and being still early in the new year, the market remains quiet," she says. "I expect we will start to see more activity as we enter into February.”</p><p>Coleman notes that national housing data from 2025 reflected a subdued market, with annual home sales declining to roughly 470,000 transactions and prices cooling modestly toward year-end. Interest rates were cut by the Bank of Canada in response to weaker demand; a move expected to support activity moving into spring 2026.</p><p>"I do expect prices to continue their downward trend for the near future," Coleman continues, "and for my clients considering selling, I encourage listing as soon as possible so as not to be chasing the market down. For buyers, this market offers some great opportunities."</p><p>Looking longer-term, Alan Nicholson, Principal and Founding Partner at <a href="https://makeprojects.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>MAKE Projects</u></a>, frames the current environment as a necessary reset.</p><p>"Development and construction in the West — BC in particular — has had decades of prosperous growth. Many have grown fat off the land. This has bred complacency, inefficiency and ineptitude into our systems," he says. "Our systems, and our skillsets, supporting policy, regulation, development, and construction, are all generally less productive. This is reflected in the retracting Canadian GDP per capita <a href="https://cabe.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/Wulong-Gu_Productivity-Performance-in-Canada.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>since 2006</u></a>."</p><p>"We need tough years; we need to lean out. Struggle makes us better. It is not easy or fun, but it is necessary," Nicholson continues. "So take heart my friends. See the moment for what it is — a necessary moment for resetting our foundation to allow for future years of returned prosperity. We will look back on these times as a distant memory where we learned to pivot, restructure, and innovate again. For me, 2026 is already filled with innovation and optimism."</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="3d75e98e5d706eec61abca79e2a317d6" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="c1fd0" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/rendering-for-make-projects-smith-campus-middle-and-secondary-school-makeprojects-ca.webp?id=63131506&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Rendering for MAKE Projects' Smith Campus Middle and Secondary School (makeprojects.ca)</small></p><p>For some developers, this reset is already translating into forward-moving momentum. </p><p>"2026 will be the year of recovery," says Rocky Sethi, Managing Director at <a href="https://strykegroup.ca/" target="_blank">STRYKE</a>. "Water cooler talk will change from,<em> 'I can't believe you are looking at buying,'</em> to<em> 'I can't believe you didn't buy that home!'</em> . With sustained pressures on construction costs, and massive pent up demand, we will start seeing inventory being absorbed, and the market will find its footing this year and pricing pressure will increase late 2026/early 2027."</p><p>"Projects that provide community will be sought after, as they provide long term value and price appreciation," Sethi explains. "At STRYKE, we believe collaboration is the key to moving forward, and we are working with key partners to deliver housing. This will include private partners, not-for-profits, and Indigenous groups whose vision and values align with our own."</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="9c89808931231acac2b5cdd92f144c9d" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="78d0e" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/rendering-for-stryke-s-innovation-district-u00a0master-planned-community-u00a0-innovationdistrict-ca.jpg?id=63131477&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Rendering for STRYKE's Innovation District Master-Planned Community (innovationdistrict.ca)</small></p><p>Indeed, resilience is a resonant theme for those willing to face today's market challenges. Vice President of Construction for <a href="https://edgardevelopment.com/" target="_blank">EDGAR Development Corporation</a>, Adam Cochrane, speaks to this sentiment of adaptation and evolution. </p><p>"While the current market makes it tough to make projects work, at EDGAR we are embracing the opportunity to roll up our sleeves, sharpen our skills, re-think how we approach developments and find cost efficiencies," Cochrane says. "It’s more important now than ever for our consultant and construction partners have that same mindset; come up with better ways of doing things that help make our pro formas work."</p><h3><span></span>The Macro Backdrop</h3><p><span></span>Zooming out, 2026 is also taking shape against a clearly defined — if still highly conditional — monetary policy backdrop.</p><p>As the year gets underway, the Bank of Canada has eight fixed interest rate decision dates <a href="https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-announcements-2026/" target="_self"><u>on the calendar</u></a>, with announcements scheduled for January 28, March 18, April 29, June 10, July 15, September 2, October 28, and December 9. Monetary Policy Reports, including updated economic and inflation forecasts, will accompany the January, April, July, and October decisions.</p><p>Following a series of rate cuts in 2025 that brought the benchmark overnight rate to 2.25%, most major Canadian banks and economists have entered 2026 expecting the Bank to maintain a steady policy stance. Recent outlooks from RBC, TD, and CIBC have pointed to moderating inflation and slower economic growth as factors supporting a prolonged hold, while National Bank and Scotiabank have suggested that modest rate increases later in the year remain possible should economic conditions strengthen or inflation prove more persistent.</p><p>And of course, industry voices are closely watching how those dynamics play out in real time. "My projection is that rates would be held all year given the current setup," Daniel Foch, Chief Real Estate Officer at <a href="https://valery.ca/" target="_blank"><u>Valery.ca</u></a>, told STOREYS this month. "But I expect the setup to change."</p><p>"I think Q4 2025 GDP data will read negative," he continued, "and Q1 2026 could as well, giving us a technical recession. I think unemployment will continue to rise, and inflation will continue to fall, and the Bank of Canada could have more runway to cut by the summer of this year."</p><p>For investors, builders, and borrowers alike, the months ahead are likely to hinge far less on any single rate decision and far more on how incoming economic data, geopolitical shifts, and on-the-ground realities reshape expectations, capacity, and what’s actually possible across the industry.</p><p>Time will tell. But for now, the prevailing 2026 sentiment is clear: it’s the Year of the Fire Horse, and while the industry isn’t galloping, it’s undeniably trotting — cautiously, deliberately, and with intention — toward what comes next.</p><p><em>______________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________</em></p><h3>Did You Get All That? The TL;DR:</h3><ul> <li><em>2026 is shaping up as a year of pressure-testing, not broad recovery — with activity returning selectively where fundamentals, pricing, and execution align. </em></li><li><em>Volatility, capital caution, and cost constraints persist, but pockets of resilience are emerging across industrial, retail, rental, and fiscally responsible, quality-led projects. </em></li><li><em>Interest rates matter, but on-the-ground realities — absorption, underwriting discipline, and demand — are increasingly driving decisions.</em></li></ul><p><em><em>______________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________</em></em></p><p style="text-align: center;">For big stories like this one right to your inbox, <a href="https://app.monstercampaigns.com/c/ufpvnvvzrshz45wflaiu/" target="_blank">sign up for our weekly newsletter</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:39:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/2026-market-outlook-canada/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/shivendu-shukla.jpg?id=63131865&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>After Years Of Remote Work, Toronto’s Office Market Is Heating Up</title><link>https://storeys.com/rto-ontario-toronto-office-market/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34015228&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C32"/><br/><br/><p>In early January, the Ford government’s return-to-office (RTO) mandate took effect, ordering 60,000 public servants back to the office. The move culminates more than a year of RTO mandates from big names in tech and finance, reaching a fever pitch in late 2025, and has put a significant amount of pressure on Toronto’s office market.</p><p>The trend is reversing years of near-stagnant activity in the downtown commercial real estate scene, which took a big hit from COVID-era work-from-home policies. And it comes as companies are advocating for increased productivity and workplace camaraderie, alongside needing to justify massive investments in costly office spaces.</p><p>But the road back to the office hasn’t been seamless. After shedding space during the pandemic, workers at some of the Big Five Banks complained about lack of desks and office space upon returning for four-day in-office weeks in the latter half of 2025. More recently, Premier Ford has acknowledged delays in providing adequate office space for public servants, calling the roadblock “a little bump.”</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adammbest/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Adam Best</u></a>, Vice President and Sales Representative at <a href="https://www.collierscanada.com/en-ca" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Colliers</u></a>, explains the shortage is due to compression from both ends. </p><p>“Demands have increased significantly, and we have no substantial new developments planned that could deliver in the next four years,” he says. At the same time, businesses have grown while also cutting down on office space during the remote-work years.</p><h3>Demand to trickle into B- and C-class</h3><p>Much of the increased demand from RTO has been concentrated in trophy and upgraded A-class office spaces, says Best. These are newer offices that are rich in amenities and well-located, particularly in the financial core and within close proximity to Union Station. But the desirability and scarcity of these trophy office spaces has created a bifurcated market. As of the last quarter, the vacancy rate for these spaces was just 3%, while older and less desirable B- and C-class offices sat around 25%, according to <a href="https://www.cbre.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>CBRE</u></a>.</p><p>Heading into 2026, this compression should eventually spill over into less desirable asset classes in Toronto, predicts <a href="https://www.avisonyoung.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>Avison Young’s</u></a> 2026 Outlook. On the ground, Best says he’s already seeing market activity trickling down into B- and even C-classes as well.</p><h3>Rents on the increase</h3><p>With trophy assets remaining limited, many tenants will struggle to expand or relocate, forecasts AV’s Outlook, incentivizing landlords to “capitalize on strong demand.”</p><p>“Some landlords are already increasing their asking rents, quarterly, if not monthly, which was the way things were back in 2019,” says Best. “We're also starting to see competing offers on space, and some of the some larger tenants are [...] securing rental rates before they continue to spike, almost like locking in your mortgage.”</p><p>According to Colliers’ Toronto Office Market Report Q4 2025, trophy rents have already increased by 21% since 2020, and are projected to rise another 20% by 2030.</p><h3>New office spaces on the horizon?</h3><p>With rents expected to rise alongside demand in 2026, there’s also cautious chatter about the possibility for new office developments. “There’s rumours of a building at Bay and Queen that might be looked at for redevelopment, plus another in the south core” says Best. “And the big one that everyone's monitoring is Oxford Development’s 30 Bay St (The Hub). That's the most likely next one to kick off.”</p><p>If it does break ground, The Hub would be the first office development to kick off since before the pandemic, highlighting just how deeply the market was impacted by remote work.</p><p>In the meantime, landlords of A- and B-class buildings have been attracting activity by upgrading their office spaces, adding new amenities and better technology to be competitive with higher asset classes. </p><h3>How retail benefits</h3><p>Beyond the office segment, retail also stands to greatly benefit from the return of in-person work, says AV’s Outlook. “As more workers return to offices in-person, restaurants, shops and service providers in the urban core will experience higher demand, creating a more dynamic environment for occupiers and investors alike,” reads the report.</p><p>Best says he’s seen the impacts of RTO on retailers first hand. “Just go to the PATH on a weekday. [...] Now you're waiting in line at a food spot for 30 minutes to an hour, in some cases,” he says. “The number of new, notable restaurants that have opened up in the past year in the financial core alone is pretty staggering. To me, that's a strong indicator of everyone's bullishness on the office market recovery.”</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:38:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/rto-ontario-toronto-office-market/</guid><dc:creator>Teagan  Sliz</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34015228&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>GTA New Home Sales Hit Historic Lows, Capping Off Worst Year On Record: Report</title><link>https://storeys.com/gta-sales-bild-altus-2025/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=53092746&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C0%2C0%2C0"/><br/><br/><p>December didn’t just close out 2025 — it underlined just how historic the year was for the GTA’s new home market.</p><p>According to the Building Industry and Land Development Association (<a href="https://www.bildgta.ca/record-low-december-new-home-sales-in-the-gta-capped-off-2025-as-the-worst-year-on-record/" target="_blank">BILD</a>), December sales capped off the worst year on record for new home sales in the GTA, raising alarms about future housing supply, job losses, and the region’s broader economic health.</p><p>December saw only 240 new home sales, a figure down 24% from December 2024 and 82% below the 10-year average, based on data from <a href="https://www.altusgroup.com/" target="_blank">Altus Group</a>, BILD's official source of new-home market intelligence. For context, a typical December would see roughly 1,327 sales. Even more striking: December 2024 had already set a record low, meaning this year’s numbers were measured against an already unusually weak benchmark.</p><p>“Never in the 45 years that new home sales data have been collected for the GTA have we seen just 5,300 sales for an entire year,” said Edward Jegg, Research Manager at Altus Group. Indeed, total sales for 2025 came in at 5,314: officially the lowest annual total on record.</p><p>Condo apartments were hit hardest. Just 87 units sold in December — down 42% year-over-year and 91% below the 10-year average. Single-family homes posted 153 sales, down 8% from last December and 59% below the long-term norm. </p><p>For the year, single-family sales totalled 3,247 (down 63% from the 10-year average), while condo apartment sales reached 2,067, an 89% shortfall.</p><p>Looking ahead, Jegg projects the same forces that weighed on buyers last year are likely to persist. "2026 is likely to see geopolitical concerns linger, prices remain elevated and the Bank of Canada has indicated the cycle of interest rate cuts has ended – thus the main drivers of buyer hesitancy are expected to drag on well into the year," said Jegg. </p><p>Inventory is also piling up. Remaining new home inventory in the GTA stood at 20,849 units in December, representing 26 months of supply based on recent sales — the highest level recorded to date.</p><p>Industry leaders warn the slowdown carries serious economic consequences. “New home sales are down well into the double digits across the province, putting 100,000 jobs at risk in Ontario alone,” said BILD COO Justin Sherwood. </p><p>"To find a comparable collapse in new home construction, you would probably have to look back to the 1940s," he continued. "New home construction is a cornerstone of our economy, yet it has effectively stalled. Now is the time to eliminate the HST on all new homes to lower the cost of housing and get buyers back into the market and the industry back to work.” </p><p>Prices, meanwhile, appear to be holding. The benchmark price for new condominium apartments sat at $1,021,235 in December, while new single-family homes averaged $1,409,725, down 9% over the past year.</p><p>Taken together, the message from December’s data is clear: the GTA’s new home market didn’t just stumble in 2025 — it stalled out entirely.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 14:44:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/gta-sales-bild-altus-2025/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=53092746&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>“No New Condo Completions” In GTHA By Decade’s End: Urbanation</title><link>https://storeys.com/condo-completions-sales-urbanation-gtha/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/dillon-kydd-unsplash.jpg?id=62979196&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>New condominium apartment sales in the Greater Toronto Hamilton Area (GTHA) fell for the fourth consecutive year, Urbanation’s year-end <a href="https://www.urbanation.ca/news/new-condo-sales-fall-4th-year-lowest-1991" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2025 Condominium Market Survey</a> shows, plunging 60% from 2024 to just 1,599 units, marking the lowest annual total since 1991. </p><p>Urbanation President Shaun Hildebrand warns that by the end of the decade, the region won't be seeing any new condo completions at all. </p><p>In 2025, sales came in 91% below the 10-year average, and down 95% from 2021 levels, the Market Survey shows. Momentum didn’t improve at year-end, either, with just 262 units sold in Q4, marking the weakest quarterly result since Q3-1990.</p><p>The slowdown has coincided with a surge in project cancellations. In 2025, a record 28 active condo projects — totalling 7,243 units — were cancelled, more than double the number of units cancelled in 2024 and well above the previous record set in 2018. Eight of those cancelled projects, representing 2,189 units, were converted to purpose-built rental, following a similar shift involving 1,434 units in 2024.</p><p>But even with those conversions, condominium construction activity declined sharply. </p><p>Purpose-built rental starts increased 24% year-over-year to 8,545 units in 2025 — marking a multi-decade high — while condo starts fell 63% to 3,272 units — a multi-decade low. Zooming out further, condo starts have dropped 88% over the past three years, resulting in a 10-year low of total inventory under construction: 50,479 units.</p><p>Last year, developers launched just 10 new condo projects in the GTHA, delivering 1,425 units to market. Only 22% of those units sold, down from 24% in 2024 and well below the 81% sales rate recorded in 2021. This lowering came despite average new-launch selling prices falling to a five-year low of $1,123 per sq. ft, down 8% from 2024 and 18% from 2022. New condos continued to sell at a premium when placed against comparable resale units, which averaged $856 per sq. ft in Q4 for condos completed within the past three years.</p><p>Urbanation reports that sales activity also shifted away from pre-construction in 2025. The year saw a record-high 33% of new condo sales occur in projects at the occupancy or registration stage, up from 9% in 2024 and 2% in 2023. Pre-construction projects accounted for less than half of new condo sales for the first time, after typically representing more than 70% of annual activity.</p><p>Completed and unsold inventory climbed accordingly. As of year-end 2025, there were 3,897 completed and unsold condo units, up 131% from a year earlier and five times higher than levels seen in 2023. Urbanation also found that approximately 10% of pre-sold condos registered in 2025 were taken back by developers after purchasers failed to close, representing roughly 3,000 units.</p><p>All of this unfolded as completions remained elevated. A total of 29,291 condo units were completed in 2025, nearly matching the record set in 2024 and running 50% above the 10-year average. Completions are expected to fall to 22,066 units in 2026 and 14,366 units in 2027. And by 2029, Urbanation says virtually no new condos are expected to be delivered.</p><p>"As the condo market enters the fifth year of its largest ever correction, the duration of this downturn should be a significant cause for concern as it relates to future supply," Hildebrand said in a release. "By the end of the decade, we know with certainty that there won’t be any new condo completions."</p><p><span></span>"What we don’t know," Hildebrand continued, "is how far into the 2030s the supply crunch will last. If rental construction can’t fill the void, this raises serious questions around the impact on affordability.”</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:50:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/condo-completions-sales-urbanation-gtha/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/dillon-kydd-unsplash.jpg?id=62979196&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>There's Still Time To Attend The Buzz Conference ‘GREATNESS 2026’</title><link>https://storeys.com/buzz-conference-greatness-2026-gta/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34015921&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Canada’s premier real estate conference returns to the GTA this month, and if you haven't snagged your ticket yet, there's still time.</p><p>On January 28 and 29, the BUZZ Conference will bring "GREATNESS 2026" to the Mississauga Convention Centre.</p><p>With a pre-conference networking event on January 27, this year's rendition of the BUZZ Conference will once again gather some of the most influential voices in Canadian real estate, from brokerage and corporate leaders to top-producing agents, teams, and technology founders.</p><p>Now more than 15 years into its flagship event series, BUZZ has built a reputation for delivering an elevated conference experience centred on human connection, practical insight, and forward-looking dialogue. </p><p>This year’s program will explore leadership, economic conditions, professionalism, marketing, and the evolving role of technology in real estate.</p><p>The speaker lineup includes Toronto Blue Jays President and CEO Mark Shapiro, who will headline the event in conversation with EXIT Realty CEO Joyce Paron, alongside an economic outlook featuring experts from CIBC, CMHC, and PwC. Senior executives from brands including RE/MAX, Royal LePage, Century 21, Coldwell Banker, and eXp Realty will also take the stage across the event's two days.</p><p>GREATNESS 2026 will be held at the Mississauga Convention Centre, with doors opening at 7:30 am each day, and opportunities for networking built in throughout the program. </p><p>Tickets include meals and all-day refreshments, as well as access to post- and pre-conference networking events.</p><p>Full event details and the complete speaker lineup are available on the BUZZ Conference website and Instagram. </p><p>Tickets are available for purchase <a href="https://www.eventbrite.ca/e/buzz-greatness-2026-by-the-buzz-conference-tickets-1287369610159" target="_blank">here</a>. </p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:47:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/buzz-conference-greatness-2026-gta/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34015921&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>STOREYS Joins SiteMedia, Elevating Canadian Real Estate Coverage</title><link>https://storeys.com/sitemedia-acquires-storeys/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/samuel-regan-unsplash.jpg?id=62826229&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>New year, same STOREYS — but better. </p><p>STOREYS is excited to announce the company has been acquired by <a href="https://www.sitemediagroup.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>SiteMedia</u></a>; a move that reflects both where the Canadian real estate industry is today, and where it's headed next.</p><p>Real estate is operating in an increasingly interconnected environment. Decisions are shaped not only by markets and policy, but by development timelines, construction realities, infrastructure investment, and long-term planning. This means that for today's (and tomorrow's) industry leaders, context matters more than ever.</p><p>Joining the SiteMedia portfolio allows STOREYS to expand that context, bringing real estate coverage into closer conversation with the broader forces shaping Canada's built environment. At the same time it remains anchored in the quality reporting, market intelligence, and in-depth analysis our readers know us for. </p><p>As STOREYS celebrates its 10-year anniversary in 2026, the months ahead will bring expanded reporting, enhanced digital media and data offerings, new events, and exclusive industry groups and communities. All of it will be built on the editorial foundation that has defined STOREYS since day one.</p><p>Alongside this evolution, there's also plenty that <em><em>won't</em></em> be changing: STOREYS remains committed to original reporting, thoughtful analysis, and stories that matter to those working within (and interested in) Canada’s housing, development, and investment landscape. </p><p>With the same voice, commitment, and focus, STOREYS remains STOREYS — now with more to offer than ever before.</p><p>The acquisition follows the <a href="https://readsitenews.com/sitenews-announces-merger-with-actual-media-to-form-sitemedia/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><u>recent merger</u></a> of SiteNews and Actual Media, marking the launch of SiteMedia as Canada’s industrial, construction, and — now with STOREYS — real estate media leader. With seven publications, nearly 60,000 executive subscribers, and a national roster of 25+ events, SiteMedia provides the scale and support that allows STOREYS to continue doing what it does best.</p><p>STOREYS is deeply proud of the last decade — and is firmly focused on what's ahead for the Canadian real estate market.</p><p>Want a deeper dive into this update? <a href="https://readsitenews.com/sitemedia-acquires-storeys-to-unify-canadas-built-community/" target="_blank"><u>Read more here</u></a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:00:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/sitemedia-acquires-storeys/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/samuel-regan-unsplash.jpg?id=62826229&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Public REITs Could Be Poised For A 2026 Comeback: Hazelview</title><link>https://storeys.com/reits-comeback-2026-hazelview-investments/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34008869&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C234%2C0%2C235"/><br/><br/><p>After spending much of the decade trailing broader equities, public real estate may finally be nearing a turning point.</p><p>That’s the view from Hazelview Investments’ newly released <a href="https://www.hazelview.com/point-of-view/thought-leadership/the-global-public-real-estate-outlook-2026" target="_blank">2026 Global Public Real Estate Outlook Report</a>, which argues that the forces shaping global REIT markets are beginning to shift. Using an active management lens, Hazelview’s public securities team points to an environment where supply, demand, valuation, and capital discipline are increasingly coming into alignment — and where the long-standing gap between public and private real estate values is becoming harder to ignore.</p> <p>Through 2025, global REITs faced trade uncertainty and shifting monetary policy, but improving financial conditions helped the asset class finish the year with a high single-digit return in local currency terms.</p><p>Results varied meaningfully by region. Japan, Hong Kong, and Singapore led returns, while Canada and the U.K. also outperformed the global benchmark. Continental Europe lagged, with the US posting the weakest performance among major regions. At the sector level, healthcare stood out on the strength of senior housing fundamentals, while cold storage, life science, data centres, and residential REITs underperformed.</p> <h3>A Cycle Nearing an Inflection Point</h3> <p>Since 2020, global REITs have underperformed broader equities, reflecting the outsized impact of the pandemic and subsequent monetary tightening on real estate. In the US, REITs have seen the largest valuation decline of any major equity segment since 2021.</p><p>Hazelview says that period of atypical performance may be nearing an end. Strengthening fundamentals, paired with what the firm views as compelling valuations, are creating conditions for REITs to begin making up lost ground in 2026 and beyond.</p> <h3>Supply, Demand, and a Valuation Disconnect</h3> <p>The outlook highlights a tightening supply backdrop across global real estate markets. New supply across major property types — including retail, industrial, residential, and office — is forecast to decline materially in most developed regions, potentially reaching all-time lows in markets such as the U.S., Europe, Canada, Australia, and parts of Asia-Pacific. Demand, meanwhile, has remained resilient, with occupancy rates trending above historical averages.</p><p>On the valuation side, Hazelview notes that global REITs are trading at multi-decade lows relative to broader equities and at a double-digit discount to intrinsic value. The firm points to rising share buybacks and privatization activity as companies respond to the persistent disconnect between public market pricing and private market asset values.</p> <h3>Looking for Opportunity</h3> <p>Against that backdrop, Hazelview points to opportunity across several segments of the public real estate market. Industrial real estate across North America, Europe, and Japan is benefiting from lower new supply and improving leasing conditions, while senior housing in North America continues to be supported by favourable demographics and constrained development.</p><p>The firm also highlights continued demand for data centres in markets such as the US, Hong Kong, and Singapore, driven in part by AI adoption. Residential real estate in Australia and Germany rounds out the picture, with supply-demand imbalances expected to support stronger rental growth.</p><p>Taken together, Hazelview’s outlook reflects a disciplined, long-term approach to public real estate investing — and a view that 2026 could mark a meaningful shift for an asset class that’s spent much of the decade on the back foot.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 21:13:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/reits-comeback-2026-hazelview-investments/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34008869&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>2025 A Strong Year for Housing Starts, But The Finish Was Uneven</title><link>https://storeys.com/2025-housing-starts-cmhc/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34013560&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Canada built more homes in 2025 than it did the year before — but the year ended with less momentum than the topline numbers might suggest.</p><p>According to the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation (CMHC), housing starts across all areas of the country reached 259,028 units in 2025, up 5.6% from 2024 and ranking as the fifth-highest annual total on record. In centres with populations of 10,000 or more, starts rose 6% year-over-year to 241,171 units, driven largely by another record-breaking year for rental construction. </p><p>For the second consecutive year, rental housing accounted for just over half of all housing starts in Canada’s urban centres.</p><p>Regionally, Canada’s six largest census metropolitan areas posted a combined 3.9% increase compared to 2024. That growth was led by record annual starts in Calgary and Edmonton, a 58% jump in Montréal, and a 12% increase in Ottawa–Gatineau, which more than offset declines in Toronto (-31%) and Vancouver (-3%).</p><p>The year ended on a strong monthly note. In December, the seasonally adjusted annual rate of housing starts rose 11% month-over-month to 282,439 units, while actual starts in centres of 10,000 or more climbed 25% year-over-year, reaching 20,716 units — the highest December total on record. Ontario was a major contributor, recording its highest monthly starts total of the year. Among the country’s three largest cities, December activity rebounded sharply, with Toronto, Montréal, and Vancouver all posting year-over-year increases, largely driven by multi-unit construction.</p><p>Still, CMHC cautions that the broader trend tells a more restrained story. </p><p>The six-month trend in housing starts — which smooths out monthly volatility — was essentially flat in December, edging down 0.1% to 264,428 units, and has been declining since September. According to CMHC Chief Economist Mathieu Laberge, most of the momentum in 2025 occurred earlier in the year, with economic uncertainty and the reduced feasibility of large residential towers pushing developers toward smaller-scale projects.</p><p>As a result, housing starts are entering 2026 from a weaker position, with CMHC flagging slowing construction momentum alongside ongoing geopolitical and trade uncertainty. </p><p>An updated Housing Market Outlook is expected in February, offering a clearer read on whether late-2025 softness is temporary — or a sign of what’s next for Canada’s housing supply pipeline.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 21:00:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/2025-housing-starts-cmhc/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34013560&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Build Canada Homes Announces What To Expect In The Year Ahead</title><link>https://storeys.com/build-canada-homes-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34014368&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Just a few short months since former Toronto Deputy Mayor Ana Bailão took the helm as CEO of <a href="https://storeys.com/build-canada-homes-federal-housing-entity-launches/" target="_blank">Build Canada Homes (BCH)</a>, the newly formed federal agency is moving from "concept to action."</p><p>In a progress update released this month, BCH revealed a robust pipeline of thousands of units slated to break ground in 2026. </p><p>The agency’s strategy centres on a "Direct Build" model — using federal lands and modern construction methods like modular and factory-built housing to bypass traditional development bottlenecks.</p><p>The Direct Build Sites The agency has issued Requests for Qualifications (RFQs) for six flagship sites across the country, representing approximately 4,000 units:</p><ul><li>Arbo (Toronto): 540 new homes at the Downsview site, with a minimum of 40% designated as affordable. This project is part of a larger $283M infrastructure investment expected to eventually catalyze 63,000 homes in the area.</li><li>Heron (Ottawa): An 18-acre site expected to accommodate 1,100 homes.</li><li>Pointe-de-Longueuil (Quebec): 1,055 homes on the St. Lawrence waterfront.</li><li>Shannon Park (Dartmouth): 630 mixed-market units in its first phase.</li><li>Naawi-Oodena (Winnipeg) & Village at Griesbach (Edmonton): Combined 675 units in partnership with Treaty One First Nations and Canada Lands Company.</li></ul><p>Beyond its own land, BCH is leveraging federal capital to incentivize municipal cooperation. A new $400M partnership with the City of Ottawa and a $300M agreement in Nova Scotia aim to unlock an additional 4,400 units. In Ottawa, the deal involves the city slashing development charges, permit fees, and property taxes to accelerate construction timelines.</p><p>"In just 100 days, we’ve gone from concept to action," Bailão said in a statement. "This is a model for how we want to work across Canada: combining speed, innovation, and collaboration to get shovels in the ground."</p><p>For the private sector, the launch of the national submission portal in late November marks a significant shift in how federal housing funds are accessed. BCH reports that proposals have already been received from every province and territory, with "hundreds more in progress."</p><p>The agency’s Investment Policy Framework prioritizes "modern methods of construction," signalling a massive federal tailwind for the modular and pre-fab industry. As BCH moves into its 2026 construction phase, the industry will be watching closely to see if this agency-led model can truly circumvent the red tape that has historically stalled "affordable" at scale.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:15:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/build-canada-homes-2026/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34014368&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Newly-Approved Underwater Nuclear Power Line Will Unlock 285,000 New GTA Homes</title><link>https://storeys.com/darlington-nuclear-line-underwater-toronto/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/wolfgang-hasselmann-unsplash.jpg?id=62823575&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Earlier this month, the Ontario government officially approved a recommendation from the Independent Electricity System Operator (IESO) to construct a new underwater transmission line that will run from the Darlington Nuclear Station directly into Toronto’s downtown core.</p><p>The project isn't just a feat of engineering; it’s a massive unlock for the real estate industry. </p><p>By expanding the city’s grid capacity, the new line is expected to provide the power necessary to support the development of approximately 285,000 new homes across the Greater Toronto Area. </p><h3>Powering the Pipeline</h3><p>For developers, the move addresses a quiet but growing "pain point" in the city-building process: grid constraints. Major high-growth pockets like Downsview, East Harbour, and the Port Lands have long been flagged as areas where ambitious residential density could eventually outpace the existing electrical infrastructure.</p><p>“As we start 2026, we are focused on strengthening Ontario’s economy and creating jobs,” Stephen Lecce, Minister of Energy and Mines, said in a release. “Without a new transmission line, Toronto would have to turn down job-creating investments and reduce housing, which is simply unacceptable. We are thinking ahead and building for the future by approving a new transmission line that will enable 285,000 new homes, power new businesses, and create thousands of jobs. We are also initiating the first IESO-led competitive transmission procurement to reduce costs and maximize benefits for families.”</p><h3>A Strategic Route</h3><p>The decision to go underwater is both a logistical and economic strategy. By bypassing the heavily congested land routes through the GTA, the underwater line minimizes community disruption and avoids the complex expropriation and permitting hurdles that typically delay major overland infrastructure projects.</p><p>The line will connect the clean energy generated at the Darlington Nuclear Station to the heart of the city, ensuring that Toronto's future high-rise clusters are powered by a low-carbon grid. The project aligns with the Darlington Nuclear Refurbishment Project and the construction of the first small modular reactors in the G7 at <a href="https://www.renewcanada.net/the-projects/darlington-new-nuclear-project/" target="_blank">Darlington New Nuclear Project</a>, the province's record investments to upgrade and expand nuclear generating capacity on-time and on-budget.</p><h3>Why It Matters</h3><p>While the project is a long-term play, its approval signals a "green light" for long-range planning in some of the city's most significant development pipelines. </p><p>The approval also follows a year of heightened focus on "social infrastructure" — the power, water, and transit required to make housing viable. By clearing the path for the Darlington-to-Toronto line, the province is attempting to ensure that the city’s vertical growth isn't stalled by a lack of juice.</p>The IESO will now move forward with the detailed planning and environmental assessment phases, with the project slated to become a cornerstone of Ontario’s long-term energy strategy, <em><em>Powering Ontario’s Growth.</em></em>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 21:08:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/darlington-nuclear-line-underwater-toronto/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/wolfgang-hasselmann-unsplash.jpg?id=62823575&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Here's The Bank Of Canada's Rate Announcement Schedule For 2026</title><link>https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-announcements-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34013749&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>As the new year gets underway, the Bank of Canada’s schedule for 2026 interest rate announcements has come into focus, with eight fixed decision dates on the calendar.</p><p>All announcements will be released at 9:45 am ET. The Bank’s <em>Monetary Policy Report</em>, which includes updated economic and inflation forecasts, will be published alongside the January, April, July, and October rate decisions. The first announcement will launch later this month, with seven following throughout the rest of the calendar year. </p><p>The full schedule for 2026 is as follows:</p> <ul> <li> Wednesday, January 28</li> <li> Wednesday, March 18</li> <li> Wednesday, April 29</li> <li> Wednesday, June 10</li> <li> Wednesday, July 15</li> <li> Wednesday, September 2</li> <li> Wednesday, October 28</li> <li> Wednesday, December 9</li></ul><p>As the new year settles in, attention is turning to how the Bank will navigate monetary policy over the year ahead, following a series of rate cuts in 2025 that brought the benchmark overnight rate to 2.25%. </p><p>While each decision will remain data-dependent, most major Canadian banks and economists have entered 2026 expecting the Bank to maintain a steady policy stance. </p><p>Recent outlooks from <a href="https://www.rbc.com/en/economics/wp-content/uploads/sites/23/2025/12/MFUDec25.pdf" target="_blank">RBC</a>, <a href="https://economics.td.com/ca-forecast-tables" target="_blank">TD</a>, and <a href="https://economics.cibccm.com/cds?id=5e81ef9f-a852-474b-ab95-f3bd6aeb3925&flag=E" target="_blank">CIBC</a> have pointed to moderating inflation and slower economic growth as factors supporting a prolonged hold. Other institutions, including <a href="https://www.nbc.ca/content/dam/bnc/taux-analyses/analyse-eco/mensuel/monthly-economic-monitor-canada.pdf" target="_blank">National Bank</a> and <a href="https://www.scotiabank.com/ca/en/about/economics/forecast-snapshot.html" target="_blank">Scotiabank</a>, have suggested that modest rate increases later in 2026 remain possible if economic conditions strengthen, or inflation proves more persistent than anticipated.</p><p>Industry insiders are also weighing in on what the year ahead may hold. </p><p>"My projection is that rates would be held all year given the current setup," says Daniel Foch, Chief Real Estate Officer at <a href="https://valery.ca/" target="_blank">Valery.ca</a>. "But I expect the setup to change."<span></span></p><p>"I think Q4 2025 GDP data will read negative," he continues, "and Q1 2026 could as well, giving us a technical recession. I think unemployment will continue to rise, and inflation will continue to fall, and the Bank of Canada could have more runway to cut by the summer of this year." </p><p>As it stands, investors and borrowers alike are closely watching upcoming economic data — and the Bank’s quarterly forecasts — for clearer signals on the path forward.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 20:46:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/bank-canada-rate-announcements-2026/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34013749&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Pent-Up Demand Poised To Nudge Canadian Home Sales Higher In 2026: CREA</title><link>https://storeys.com/crea-quarterly-forecast-january-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/peter-robbins-unsplash.jpg?id=62812380&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Canada’s resale housing market is expected to regain some forward momentum in 2026, following a stop-start recovery that took shape over the back half of last year, according to the <a href="https://www.crea.ca/housing-market-stats/canadian-housing-market-stats/quarterly-forecasts/" target="_blank">latest forecast</a> from the Canadian Real Estate Association (CREA). </p><p>Updated on January 15, CREA’s outlook revises expectations for 2026 and extends the national forecast through 2027, painting a picture of a market that is stabilizing rather than surging. While 2025 ultimately proved slower than initially anticipated — weighed down by economic uncertainty tied to U.S. tariff threats — much of that softness was concentrated early in the year. Beginning in April, sales activity rallied, climbing 12% by August before settling into a holding pattern through year-end.</p><p>That mid-year rebound is expected to resume in 2026, supported largely by pent-up demand, particularly among first-time buyers who have been sidelined for much of the past four years. CREA notes that while interest rates haven’t declined as much as many prospective buyers hoped, they have likely fallen far enough to restore a degree of attainability. The Bank of Canada’s October 29, 2025 signal — that rates were likely as low as they were going to get — is expected to further encourage borrowers who had been waiting on the sidelines.</p><p>Nationally, CREA forecasts that 494,512 residential properties will change hands via MLS® Systems in 2026, representing a 5.1% increase from 2025. British Columbia and Ontario are expected to lead that recovery, with sales in both provinces forecast to rise by more than 8%, reflecting the greater room for improvement following deeper slowdowns. </p><p>Elsewhere, gains are expected to be more modest, as activity in many provinces is already running closer to historical norms and supply remains constrained.</p><p>The national average home price is forecast to increase 2.8% in 2026 to $698,881. Price growth is expected to be more subdued in B.C., Alberta, Ontario, and Nova Scotia, while Saskatchewan, Quebec, and Newfoundland and Labrador are forecast to see comparatively stronger gains. Even so, CREA anticipates a notable cooling in those hotter markets, with price growth slowing from the 6% - 8% range in 2025 to between 3% and 6% in 2026.</p><p>Looking ahead to 2027, national home sales are forecast to rise another 3.5% to 511,966, again led by B.C. and Ontario. Average prices are expected to edge up 2.3% year-over-year to $714,991, marking the seventh consecutive year the national average has hovered near the $700,000 mark.</p><p>CREA will release its next quarterly forecast on April 16, 2026.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:29:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/crea-quarterly-forecast-january-2026/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/peter-robbins-unsplash.jpg?id=62812380&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Rentsync Announces Acquisition Of Urbanation</title><link>https://storeys.com/rentsync-acquires-urbanation/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=60551501&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C52%2C0%2C52"/><br/><br/><p>Toronto-based software and data company Rentsync has announced its acquisition of Urbanation, bringing together two well-known players in Canada’s rental housing and real estate data ecosystem.</p><p>Rentsync shared the news Wednesday, January 14, explaining the move will significantly strengthen its market intelligence capabilities and deliver more comprehensive insights into Canada’s rental housing market.</p><p>Urbanation, founded more than four decades ago, is widely regarded as one of the country’s most trusted sources of real estate research and consulting, with a focus on rental housing and condos. Its data and analysis are used by developers, investors, lenders, operators, and policymakers navigating a housing market defined by supply constraints, affordability pressures, and shifting development cycles.</p><p>“I am pleased to announce the strategic sale of Urbanation, a company I founded and grew over the past four decades and has become the industry leader for real estate market data and insights,” Eve Lewis, Founder and CEO of Urbanation, said in a release. “I am confident that the strong foundation, values and integrity we established will lead to even more success as Urbanation combines forces with Rentsync.”</p><p>The two companies are not new to working together. Over the past three years, Rentsync and Urbanation have partnered to publish the monthly <em>Rentals.ca National Rent Report, </em>and to build a comprehensive rental market database covering the Greater Golden Horseshoe, Ottawa, and Montreal. </p><p>Under the new ownership structure, Urbanation President Shaun Hildebrand will continue to lead data and market analytics.</p><p>“The integration of Urbanation into Rentsync represents an important milestone for Canada’s residential real estate sector,” Hildebrand said in the release. “Purpose-built rentals and condominiums will take on an increasingly larger role in helping to expand housing supply and improve housing affordability across the country. Never has there been a greater need for transparent and accurate data, granular insights, and high-level market guidance to shape the future of how the market operates.”</p><p>Rentsync says the acquisition supports its broader goal of building an integrated platform that spans the full rental housing lifecycle. Together, Rentsync, Urbanation, and the Rentals.ca network of listing sites will combine market intelligence, renter demand data, digital marketing, and property management software to support investment decision-making, leasing, and asset performance.</p><p>“Canada is geographically massive and there is no single national source of truth for well-researched, reliable, housing real estate data,” said Max Steinman, CEO of Rentsync. “This acquisition brings us one step closer to solving that problem. Urbanation has an outstanding reputation and we will preserve that legacy while helping to grow the brand quickly across the country.”</p><p>The Urbanation deal follows closely on Rentsync’s December 2025 acquisition of Spacelist, and marks the company’s second acquisition since receiving investment from Silversmith Capital Partners in April 2025. Rentsync says it remains focused on growth — through product development and strategic acquisitions — as it works to simplify and optimize the leasing experience across Canada — and beyond.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 18:42:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/rentsync-acquires-urbanation/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=60551501&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Opinion: Toronto Is Experiencing A Silent Housing Boom</title><link>https://storeys.com/toronto-housing-boom-missing-middle/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/felipe-moura-unsplash.jpg?id=62701918&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p style="text-align: center;"><em>This article was written and submitted by Noam Hazan, licensed architect and principal of <a href="https://www.noamhazan.com/" target="_blank">Noam Hazan Design Studio</a>, a Toronto based architecture & Interior design studio specializing in new single-family homes and missing middle housing.</em></p><p>Toronto is sleepwalking into a housing solution and most people do not even see it.</p><p>While headlines fixate on condo weakness and stalled launches, a different kind of real estate boom is already underway in Toronto neighbourhoods. It is not driven by Bay Street developers or glossy sales centres. It is driven by regular Torontonians. Homeowners. Realtors. Professionals with day jobs. First time “citizen developers” who are building gentle density on ordinary streets. And it is happening right now.</p><p>My view is simple. The missing middle is the most alive part of Toronto real estate today, and it is quietly building the kind of housing the city actually needs.</p><p>I am a licensed architect in Toronto and run a boutique practice focused on missing middle housing. Since the city expanded permissions for multiplexes and garden suites, our work has surged. Many architects are complaining the market is slow. In our niche, it is the opposite. The phone rings because this is one of the few lanes where projects still move.</p><p>The policy change was not complicated, but its impact has been dramatic. In May 2023, Toronto approved citywide permissions for multiplex housing, allowing duplexes, triplexes and fourplexes across residential neighbourhoods. Garden suites have also taken off. In June 2025, Council went further by allowing sixplex permissions in nine wards.</p><p>Those are planning decisions. But the results show up in permits and construction sites.</p><p>City data shows this is already happening at scale. In the first 18 months after the May 2023 change, Toronto issued 452 multiplex building permits. Garden suites are moving just as quickly: by May 8, 2025, the City reported 812 applications received and 480 permits issued. That’s not a fringe experiment, it’s an active pipeline. The practical effect is that any single home lot may now be able to support a fourplex plus a garden suite, and in certain wards, up to a sixplex, provided the site is zoned ‘Residential’. </p><p>Here is the part most people misunderstand. This boom is not being driven by “developers” in the traditional sense, but rather what is now being call the ‘citizen developer’.</p><p>One of our clients is a young family building a multiplex and planning to live in one unit. They are not flipping. They are building a future and creating housing at the same time.</p><p>Another is made up of three Toronto executives who left high paid corporate jobs to start a small development firm focused on small purpose-built multiplex rentals. Their model is repeatable projects which are scaled to conform to the new multiplex bylaws. </p><p>Another is a logistics entrepreneur who sold his company and decided to develop properties he already owned. Another is a realtor who watched clients do these projects, saw the opportunity, and decided to do it himself. </p><p>I did too. I am currently developing my own fourplex and garden suite because I wanted to test the model personally, and because I believe that it’s the only real estate investment in Toronto that actually makes sense right now.</p><p>This is what a housing movement looks like when it is led by citizens. It is messy, it is local, it is practical, and it is growing!</p><p>It also has a community behind it that feels almost like a subculture. I am in a WhatsApp group with 373 members. Architects, builders, lenders, planners, realtors and aspiring developers who trade notes daily. They share lessons, swap contractor recommendations and compare costs. They help each other avoid expensive mistakes. </p><p>Just with a simple search on Eventbrite, you will also find a range of ‘Missing Middle conferences’ that draw relatively large crowds, often in the hundreds.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="0cb841b1e24a043dd828e4c723fb5994" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="2bd98" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/noam-hazan-design-studio.png?id=62701896&width=980"/> <small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Noam Hazan Design Studio</small></p><p>There is also a solid financial reason this continues even in a down market. Many of these projects are rentals, and rentals are underwritten differently than condos. Once you reach five or more units (for example a fourplex and Garden suite), you can tap insured multi unit financing pathways, including CMHC’s MLI Select program. MLI Select can reward qualifying projects with lower insurance premiums and longer amortization periods. That matters when interest rates and construction costs have squeezed feasibility.</p><p>Then there is the tax piece, which changes the equation for purpose built rentals. The federal government introduced a 100% rebate of the GST or the federal portion of the HST for eligible new purpose built rental housing, and CRA guidance indicates that Ontario’s provincial rebate can also be 100% for qualifying projects. In plain language, for projects that qualify, the HST hit can be largely recovered. That is not a rounding error. That is real money.</p><p>Toronto does not have a housing supply problem only because we do not build enough. Toronto has a housing supply problem because we tell ourselves the only way to build is through mega projects. Towers or nothing, and that thinking is wrong. It leaves housing production in the hands of a few large players. When they slow down, the entire city slows down.</p><p>The missing middle is proof there is another way. Thousands of small decisions, hundreds of projects, and lots of people building five, six, seven homes where there used to be one. Not everywhere. Not overnight. But steadily.</p><p>If you want to understand where Toronto housing is actually being built right now, stop staring at the skyline. Start looking at the side streets. The boom is already here. Most people just have not noticed.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/toronto-housing-boom-missing-middle/</guid><dc:creator>Guest Author</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/felipe-moura-unsplash.jpg?id=62701918&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Beyond The Forecasts: A Framework For Understanding GTA Real Estate In 2026</title><link>https://storeys.com/gta-real-estate-2026-framework/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/nano-do-unsplash.jpg?id=62694765&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p style="text-align: center;"><em>This article was written and submitted by <a href="https://www.clre.ca/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Cameron Levitt</a>, a Toronto-based <a href="https://storeys.com/real-estate-agent-meaning-definition-real-estate/" target="_self">real estate agent</a> with RE/MAX Hallmark who writes about housing dynamics, <a href="https://storeys.com/market-trends-meaning-definition-real-estate/" target="_self">market trends</a>, and the Canadian economy.</em></p><p><em><br/></em></p><p>Every new year brings a surge of real estate predictions and forecasts. They will all attempt to boil down the market into average prices and sales volumes. This isn't a forecast. It's a framework to cut through those forecasts and interpret what the actual data reveals as 2026 unfolds.</p><p>The structure of the GTA real estate market has fundamentally shifted. If you're looking to navigate housing decisions in 2026, you need to know what's driving the market and what signals to watch as the year unfolds. The market has fragmented, and how we talk about it needs to change accordingly.</p><h3>A Fragmented Market</h3><p>For years we got used to the idea of the GTA real estate market moving as a cohesive whole. In reality, it's always been a collection of micro markets across different areas, price points, and housing types. It was accurate enough to say real estate overall operated in a "rising tide lifts all boats" environment, but higher interest rates shattered the cohesive market. Aggregate statistics now show lower prices, lower volume, and higher inventory, but these measures obscure what's happening across different micro-markets. Some segments remain stable with strong demand and tight supply, while others have distressed sellers and frozen activity. Most fall somewhere in between. </p><h3>Structural Changes to Buyers and Sellers</h3><p>In the absence of extremely cheap credit, wealth dictates market participation. It enables buying and removes urgency to sell, while a lack of it can force selling and prevents buying. Who participates in the market and how they behave has shifted notably.</p><p>The buyer pool has shrunk and become far more selective, driving persistently low sales volume. The most critical change is that investor and speculator demand has effectively disappeared. The math doesn't work anymore, and the momentum-chasing behaviour has stopped. This has removed a massive source of demand that operated independently of end-user housing needs. The impact concentrates in segments that absorbed heavy investor activity during the run-up: condos, entry-level price points, and secondary locations.</p><p>What remains is end-user demand from people buying a home to live in, and that pool has also shrunk. Higher mortgage rates automatically exclude a whole cohort of people who would like to purchase a home but can no longer qualify. The buyers who can still participate tend to be higher income professionals, often with accumulated wealth or family support. They make decisions based on lifestyle fit and long-term usability rather than pure investment potential. Their preferences funnel demand toward a narrow band: well-located, turnkey homes that require minimal work. Everything outside those segments faces far weaker competition.</p><p>On the seller side, the picture inverts. The seller base has increased. Much of this comes from investors exiting positions and owners deleveraging under dramatically higher mortgage payments. These sellers concentrate in specific sectors and locations: primarily areas that absorbed heavy investor demand during the run-up, entry-level price points where buyers are now priced out, and properties purchased by people without significant prior equity. These are the segments where sellers face the harshest reality, competing against other distressed or motivated sellers for a dramatically smaller buyer pool than when they purchased. Some segments have tight inventory and strong demand while others are flooded with listings chasing a much smaller pool of qualified buyers.</p><h3>Average Price: Why Aggregates Mislead</h3><p>For the past 3 years since our market fragmented, Toronto has been stable and range-bound, oscillating in a seasonal pattern above the 2020 levels.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="f2c50e0a9084c70c2db9dbe254c71005" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="4b13b" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.gif?id=62673980&width=980"/> </p><p>The broader TRREB area, which includes Durham, Halton, Peel, and York regions, shows a clear declining trend since the 2022 peak. One market held while the other declined, yet both get averaged together into a single "GTA average price" that obscures this divergence entirely.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="7add8ce12849eefb60aa4eeeceaf8a8b" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="63e91" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.gif?id=62673401&width=980"/> </p><p style="text-align: left;">Location matters most, followed by state of repair, renovation quality, and long-term usability operating as equally important factors. Properties in established, well-located areas generally held value while secondary locations weakened. Location provides a floor even for neglected properties. A rundown home in a prime area may still attract buyers willing to invest in restoration for long-term location value, albeit at discount.</p><p>Condition operates on two levels: state of repair and aesthetic appeal. Deferred maintenance on major systems like roofs, windows, and mechanical elements create severe penalties that updated finishes can't overcome. The buyers for fixer-uppers were often speculators looking for renovation projects, and that demand is gone. </p><p>Beyond condition, long-term usability is equally important. End user buyers distinguish between properties that check boxes on paper and good homes they can actually live in for decades. The number of bedrooms means nothing if the rooms are unusable, parking doesn't help if it's inaccessible, and layout matters more than square footage. The selective buyer pool drives this uneven price performance. Properties that satisfy these priorities hold value while those that don't decline. These patterns of price divergence illustrate how the market operates at the segment level through a sorting mechanism that average prices obscure entirely. <br/><br/>When evaluating 2026 forecasts and data, focus on what's happening in specific micro-markets, not aggregate price movements. Toronto prices could push higher while suburban weakness drags down the overall TRREB average, masking a recovery. If the divergence narrows, the wealth-based sorting is easing. If it widens, those structural forces are intensifying.</p><h3>Sales Volume: Is the Buyer Pool Actually Expanding?</h3><p style="">While average price reveals where value is holding or declining across segments, sales volume directly reflects the size of the active buyer pool. For volume to grow meaningfully, either affordability has to improve, or sentiment has to shift enough to bring willing participants off the sidelines.</p><p style="">Affordability improvements are most likely to come from lower prices. Lower interest rates could also bring marginalized buyers back into qualification range, but the Bank of Canada has signalled it's on hold. Wealth effects from other asset markets matter only for the asset-owning cohort. </p><p style="">Sentiment shifts could come from several sources. The Canadian economy showed surprising resilience with modest growth through the end of 2025, and if that continues it could rebuild confidence. Clarity on the U.S. trade situation, which caused significant sentiment shock in 2025, could also remove a major source of uncertainty. The clarity that rates won't drop further might bring fence-sitters to act once "waiting for better conditions" loses its logic. Media coverage also directly shapes buyer psychology, so changes in how the media frames the housing market could help to shift sentiment.</p><p style="">The critical question isn't just whether volume grows, but which segments see the growth. Growth concentrated only in premium segments signals the wealth-based sorting continues, whether from the same narrow pool getting more active or from improving conditions for the asset-owning class. Volume growth in lower-priced segments would show that affordability improvements or sentiment shifts are bringing marginalized buyers back into the market, not just activating the wealthy cohort that could already transact.</p><h3>Inventory Levels: Understanding Supply?</h3><p>Along with average price and sales volume, the other metric quoted constantly is inventory; the number of listings for sale. These three tell the complete story: volume shows the size of the buyer pool, inventory shows the supply of available choices, and price shows how those two forces sort themselves out in the market.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image"> <img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="6f34ab2abd4ebeb8e470e63a7ec2d501" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="fbd11" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.gif?id=62674012&width=980"/> </p><p>For the past four years, inventory has followed a clear pattern: higher highs and higher lows, even accounting for seasonal variation. Whether this continues, flattens, or reverses in 2026 signals important market dynamics.</p><p>Total inventory matters, but segment-level breakdown reveals more. Condos may continue building inventory while houses flatten, or new supply may concentrate in specific locations or price points. If the four-year pattern breaks with lower highs or lower lows compared to previous years, supply forces are easing. If it continues climbing, those forces persist.</p><p>A common misconception is that the surge in listings only signals distressed and urgent sellers, but the reality is more nuanced. Rising inventory reflects both expanded supply and slower absorption. More sellers are entering the market through investor exits and forced deleveraging. At the same time, absorption has slowed as properties in weaker segments sit longer without buyers.</p><p>Many listings sit on the market at aspirational prices from sellers who would like to sell but don't need to. Truly motivated sellers have to meet the market where buyers see value. Properties that languish on market at firm pricing may eventually see price cuts as sellers exhaust their patience, or they simply withdraw and wait. How this plays out depends on the broader economic landscape.</p><h3>The Operating Context</h3><p>All of this operates within a specific constraint: the overall health of the Canadian economy. Economists are forecasting modest economic growth in 2026, with significant uncertainty remaining. If that scenario materializes, the structural dynamics persist. If growth meaningfully exceeds or falls short of expectations, the framework still applies by adjusting which direction the pressure moves.</p><p>The market follows established seasonal patterns. Without significant fundamental shifts like dramatic rate changes or major economic developments, 2026 will likely maintain this rhythm. Don't confuse predictable seasonal movements with market shifts. A summer price dip or winter slowdown is the calendar, not a signal.<br/><br/>Throughout 2026, you'll see forecasts and monthly data attempting to capture market direction in a single number. Use this framework to evaluate what those statistics reveal. The GTA market operates by segment, driven by selective buyers, varied seller motivations, and wealth-based sorting. Understanding these forces matters more than tracking aggregate trends. How this applies depends on your position in the market.</p><h3>What This Means For You</h3><p><strong><em>For Buyers: </em></strong>Don't expect broad market weakness to create opportunity in the segments you actually want. Discounts concentrate in compromised inventory — properties requiring work, less desirable locations, functional issues. Premium segments stay competitive regardless of headlines. Negotiating leverage comes from individual seller motivation and extended days on market, not from market narratives.</p><p><strong><em>For Sellers: </em></strong>Sellers outside premium segments face downward pressure. Aspirational pricing gets punished with extended days on market and eventual price cuts below where proper pricing would have landed. Professional presentation, proper pricing strategy, and honest assessment of your competitive position are required to transact efficiently.</p><p><strong><em>For Buy-and-Sell Movers: </em></strong>Transacting in two different micro-markets, which may be acting very differently, can expose you to significant transactional and financial risk. Understanding which segment you're selling in and which you're buying into determines how you structure the deals to keep yourself protected. It is crucial to work with someone who evaluates both sides of your move specifically, not someone applying a standard strategy regardless of your situation.</p><p><strong><em>For Homeowners Not Planning to Move: </em></strong>Take care of your house. Buyers today are end-users prioritizing turnkey properties, and they view deferred maintenance as costs significantly higher than the actual repair expense. Protecting your home's value now means actively maintaining it, not passively assuming appreciation will cover neglect. </p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:35:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/gta-real-estate-2026-framework/</guid><dc:creator>Guest Author</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/nano-do-unsplash.jpg?id=62694765&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>GTA Housing Market Ends 2025 More Affordable, But Confidence Remains Key</title><link>https://storeys.com/trreb-housing-market-january-2026/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/teunard-droog-unsplash.png?id=62681633&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>As 2025 drew to a close, <a href="https://trreb.ca/2025-ends-with-more-affordable-market-and-paves-the-way-for-year-of-recovery/" target="_blank">new data</a> from the Toronto Regional Real Estate Board (TRREB) painted a picture of a market still under pressure, but notably more affordable than it was a year earlier — a shift that, according to the board, may help lay the groundwork for recovery in the year ahead.</p><p>Annual GTA home sales declined in 2025 amid ongoing economic uncertainty, as buyers remained cautious in the face of broader concerns around employment and the cost of living. Over the same period, however, elevated listing inventory gave buyers greater negotiating power, contributing to lower selling prices and improved affordability across the region.</p><p>For the full calendar year, GTA REALTORS® reported 62,433 home sales through TRREB’s MLS® System, representing an 11.2% decline compared to 2024. New listings moved in the opposite direction, rising 10.1% year-over-year to 186,753. The annual average selling price for 2025 came in at $1,067,968, down 4.7% from $1,120,241 in 2024.</p><p>According to TRREB President Daniel Steinfeld, the combination of lower selling prices and declining mortgage rates helped improve affordability over the course of the year, positioning the market for a potential rebound once consumer confidence improves. Steinfeld noted that sales activity is likely to increase when households feel more assured about economic conditions and the strength of the labour market, allowing pent-up demand to begin flowing back into the market.</p><p>December’s figures echoed the broader annual trend. The month saw 3,697 home sales, down 8.9% from December 2024, while new listings edged up 1.8% year-over-year to 5,299. The MLS® Home Price Index (HPI) Composite benchmark declined 6.3% compared to a year earlier, while the average selling price fell 5.1% to $1,006,735.</p><p>On a seasonally adjusted basis, December sales dipped slightly compared to November, as new listings continued to rise. While the MLS® HPI Composite trended marginally lower month-over-month, the average selling price saw a modest increase.</p><p>Looking ahead, TRREB Chief Information Officer Jason Mercer pointed to the importance of stable economic conditions in supporting a sustained recovery. Mercer emphasized that households need confidence in their employment prospects before taking on long-term mortgage commitments, even in a more affordable market environment.</p><p>Meanwhile, TRREB CEO John DiMichele is calling on governments to provide tax relief and address rising living costs, framing affordability challenges as part of a broader economic issue. According to DiMichele, easing financial pressure on households could help restore confidence and support more stable housing demand as the market moves forward into 2026.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:01:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/trreb-housing-market-january-2026/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/png" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/teunard-droog-unsplash.png?id=62681633&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Minto Group, Crestpoint Strike $2.3B Deal To Take Minto Apartment REIT Private</title><link>https://storeys.com/minto-group-crestpoint-private-reit/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34008065&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C66%2C0%2C67"/><br/><br/><p>Minto Group and Crestpoint Real Estate Investments have announced the formation of a new joint venture partnership alongside a $2.3-billion take-private transaction involving Minto Apartment REIT.</p><p>Under the agreement, Crestpoint will acquire all outstanding units of Minto Apartment REIT not already owned by Minto and certain senior executives for $18.00 per unit in cash. The transaction values the REIT at approximately $2.3 billion, including the assumption of net debt and retained equity interests held by Minto and affiliated parties.</p><p>The deal will see Minto retain a significant ownership stake in the newly formed partnership, which is intended to operate as a long-term, programmatic platform focused on the ownership, operation, and development of purpose-built rental housing across Canada. The partnership will primarily target newer-generation multi-family assets, while also considering select value-add, repositioning, and co-development opportunities over time.</p><p>The combined platform will concentrate on major Canadian markets, including Toronto, Vancouver, Calgary, Montreal, Ottawa, Victoria, Halifax, and select GTA-adjacent areas. Property management will be provided by Minto, with Crestpoint and Minto jointly overseeing asset management. </p><p>Minto will also lead development and construction management on future projects that align with the partnership’s investment criteria.</p><p>"Minto is excited to announce this strategic transaction and partnership with Crestpoint – a best-in-class real estate investor with a shared vision and commitment to long-term success," said Michael Waters, Chief Executive Officer of Minto Group. "We believe that this partnership will best enable Minto to execute on its strategic initiatives moving forward, while ensuring the company remains true to the core values it has upheld for over 70 years."</p><p>"We are thrilled and proud to announce this new partnership and transaction with Minto," said Kevin Leon, President & Chief Executive Officer of Crestpoint. "This transaction will significantly enhance our multi-family exposure across the country while allowing us to work and grow alongside a successful and reputable partner that has decades of experience in the sector."</p><p>TD Securities is acting as exclusive financial advisor to the partners, with Torys LLP serving as legal counsel. McCarthy Tétrault LLP is acting as legal counsel to Crestpoint.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:50:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/minto-group-crestpoint-private-reit/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34008065&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>What's Open And Closed In Toronto On New Year's Day</title><link>https://storeys.com/new-years-day-2026-toronto/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=50943449&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C0%2C0%2C0"/><br/><br/><p>Even if you weren't much of a planner in 2025, the new year is your chance to start on a better foot. </p><p>At the very least, we recommend planning ahead for New Year's Day, which falls on Wednesday this year and is a statutory holiday. As such, banks and government services will be closed, however, some malls, grocery stores, and attractions will be open, albeit with special hours. Here's what you need to know.</p><h3>What's Closed On New Year's Day</h3><ul><li>Banks</li><li>Canada Post</li><li>Government offices and services</li><li>Libraries</li><li>Most grocery stores</li><li>LCBO</li><li>Beer Store</li><li>Dufferin Mall</li><li>Scarborough Town Centre</li><li>Sherway Gardens</li><li>Shops at Don Mills</li><li>St. Lawrence Market</li><li>Yorkdale Mall</li><li>Hockey Hall of Fame</li></ul><h3>What's Open On New Year's Day</h3><p><strong>Transit</strong></p><ul><li>The TTC will operate on <a href="https://www.ttc.ca/routes-and-schedules/Service-details-and-holidays" target="_blank">Sunday service</a></li><li>GO Transit will operate on a <a href="https://www.gotransit.com/en/see-schedules/holiday-schedules" target="_blank">Saturday schedule</a></li></ul><div><strong>Shopping</strong></div><ul> <li>Bramalea City Centre — 11 am to 6 pm</li><li><span></span>CF Markville — 11 am to 6 pm</li><li><span></span>CF Toronto Eaton Centre — 12 pm to 7 pm</li><li><span></span>Promenade Mall – 10 am to 6 pm</li><li><span></span>Square One Shopping Centre — 11 am to 6 pm</li><li><span></span>Toronto Premium Outlets – 9:30 am to 7 pm</li><li><span></span>Vaughan Mills – 10 am to 6 pm</li><li>Select Shoppers Drug Mart <a href="https://www.shoppersdrugmart.ca/en/store-locator" target="_blank">locations</a></li><li>Select Rexall <a href="https://www.rexall.ca/storelocator/" target="_blank">locations</a></li><li>Select Wine Rack <a href="https://www.winerack.com/stores" target="_blank">locations</a></li></ul><div></div><p><strong>Grocery</strong></p><ul><li>Loblaws — 60 Carlton Street: 8am to 8pm</li><li>Rabba Fine Foods — all locations open 24 hours</li><li>Summerhill Market — all locations open 10 am to 7 pm</li><li>Whole Foods — 87 Avenue Road: 10 am to 9 pm</li></ul><div><strong>Attractions</strong></div><ul> <li><span></span>Aga Khan Museum — 10 am to 5:30 pm</li><li>The Art Gallery of Ontario — 10:30 am to 4 pm</li><li>Royal Ontario Museum — 10 am to 5:30 pm</li><li>Casa Loma — 10 am to 5 pm</li><li>Canada's Wonderland (Winterfest) — 3 pm to 9 pm</li><li>CN Tower — 11 am to 8 pm</li> <li> High Park Zoo — 9 am to 5 pm</li> <li> Ripley’s Aquarium — 9 am to 11 pm</li><li>Riverdale Farm — 9 am to 5 pm</li><li>Toronto Zoo — 9:30 am to 4:30 pm</li><li>Toronto Island ferries</li><li>Movie theatres</li></ul>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 14:19:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/new-years-day-2026-toronto/</guid><dc:creator>STOREYS Editorial Team</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=50943449&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Toronto Approves Revised Plans For Wilson Heights 'Housing Now' Site</title><link>https://storeys.com/housing-now-development-approval/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365990&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=4%2C0%2C5%2C0"/><br/><br/><p>
	At Tuesday's Toronto City Council meeting, councillors approved the Zoning By-law Amendment application for Block 1 of 50 Wilson Heights Boulevard — one portion of a larger City-led Housing Now initiative to deliver 1,484 new residential units, including 520 affordable rentals, to Wilson Avenue and Allen Road.
</p><p>
	Led by the City's real estate agency, CreateTO, the eight-acre community aims to replace an underused surface-level TTC commuter parking lot with affordable, market rental, and ownership homes in close proximity to Wilson Station. The site sits to the north of Wilson Avenue between Allen Road and Wilson Heights Boulevard in Clanton Park, just south of the <a href="https://storeys.com/downsview-west-district-8800-homes/" target="_blank">Downsview development lands</a>.
</p><iframe allowfullscreen="" height="450" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2882.7787635664768!2d-79.4493215!3d43.7359226!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x882b3238b3fcc17b%3A0xaf1b4643661454f0!2s50%20Wilson%20Heights%20Blvd%2C%20Toronto%2C%20ON%20M3H%201V6!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sca!4v1734538428171!5m2!1sen!2sca" style="border:0;" width="600"></iframe><p>
	The multi-phase community is made up of four blocks, the first of which is now approved for 209 housing units, up from the 206 previously proposed in 2021, and 10 storeys, down from the original 12. Behind the height reduction is the elimination of 43,109 sq. ft of office space nixed in response to evolving office needs in the City. Other changes include slightly reduced vehicle and bicycle parking, as well as the removal of a publicly accessible open space (POPS).
</p><p>
	Block 1, which is being developed by <a href="https://www.greenwin.ca/" target="_blank">Greenwin</a> and <a href="https://www.tridel.com/?utm_source=google&utm_medium=cpc&gad_source=1&gclid=CjwKCAiAgoq7BhBxEiwAVcW0LPJhEQl6pR2LG3BIJr9YI_We9ZDyK_G45MRZpTDSILSxcml2-tzH6hoCJtgQAvD_BwE" target="_blank">Tridel</a>, and designed by <a href="https://kirkorarchitects.com/" target="_blank">Kirkor Architects</a>, is located on the western portion of the site, edging onto Allen Road and Wilson Avenue and spanning 42,518 sq. ft. This section of the master-planned community is envisioned as a mixed-use development, alongside Block 2, with the rest being primarily residential buildings.</p><p>
	Plans depict an eight-storey tower atop a two-storey podium with a terrace provided on the roof of level two. At grade 2,960 sq. ft of retail space is proposed, as well as 4,499 sq. ft of indoor and 4736 sq. ft of outdoor amenity space.</p><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="dd4ac1037b3206a2d5dc69054753ba61" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="b5fdf" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365978&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="a5cb3f17c4b4671e700630f8b2fbc6cc" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="20633" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365981&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="af1be431a0a0f5e5342760d93328faa7" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="e74a7" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365979&width=980"/><h3></h3><br/><img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="84a0c6f2ac9689ba8198519272c23e6f" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="31c1c" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365980&width=980"/><p>For the unit breakdown, there will be 155 one-bedrooms, 36 two bedrooms, and 18 three-bedrooms. And as for parking, vehicular spaces have been reduced from 159 to 155 and bicycle parking has been reduced from 230 to 209 spaces.</p><p>Additionally, Block 1 included a portion of the site known as Block 9, which has been created for the existing sewer lands running along Allen Road. </p><p>Once complete, Block 1 will represent the first step in realizing a vibrant master-planned community offering 1,484 new housing units, a park, a child-care centre, and public community spaces. The project is joined by 19 other sites allocated by the City for housing development.</p><p>“Our vision for Toronto is to see families live, work and thrive without having to worry about securing affordable rents, accessing transit or finding childcare or green spaces for kids to play," Mayor Olivia Chow said at the Wilson Heights <a href="https://www.toronto.ca/news/city-of-toronto-and-createto-break-ground-on-new-mixed-use-transit-oriented-housing-project-with-520-affordable-rental-homes/" target="_blank">groundbreaking ceremony</a>, held in late-November. "This transit-oriented community brings all of these elements together, creating a sensible and replicable model for city-building."</p><p>Construction has begun with the process of dismantling the parking lot and, as of now, first occupancy is expected to begin in early-2029.</p><p><em>Note: renderings reflect 2021 building plans.</em></p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 17:27:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/housing-now-development-approval/</guid><dc:creator>Teagan  Sliz</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/png" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.png?id=55365990&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Serious Shortage Of Seniors' Housing Motivates BC Developer</title><link>https://storeys.com/senior-housing-shortage-darwin-northshore/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/darwin-properties-under-construction-seniors-residence.jpg?id=35232440&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Developer Oliver Webbe hadn’t realized the serious shortfall of seniors' housing until earlier this year, when his own parents-in-law could no longer live independently due to health issues.<br/></p><p>The Chief Executive Officer of Darwin Group says he and some of his friends are seeing parents in sudden need of assisted living care, and they are realizing the serious lack.</p><p>In his case, his in-laws, a former school principal and former nurse, lived comfortably in a two-bedroom condo in North Vancouver, living independently until shortly after Christmas, when they suddenly needed assisted living. But because they owned their home, the elderly couple didn’t qualify for low-cost subsidized housing. It meant they had to fork out more than $15,000 a month to a private care home — the only unit available on the Northshore. </p><p>Webbe’s mother-in-law died recently, so his father-in-law is left on his own, spending his life savings on end-of-life care. And because there isn’t rent control legislation to protect this type of seniors' housing from increases, management could raise their rent next month, he says. </p><p>“I’ve lived on the Northshore most of my life and I’m 43 years old, and most of my friends are starting to experience this with their parents,” he says. “We are starting to see this as a common conversation my friends are having all of a sudden, due to health conditions, mental health and Alzheimer’s, we are now starting to look around for facilities that our parents could move into… And we are shocked with how expensive it is.”</p><p>Darwin’s 6.6-acre Lonsdale Square development in the city of North Vancouver includes a seniors' assisted living facility with a memory care unit. Operated by Sunrise Senior Living, the six-storey facility will include 100 units for assisted living and memory care. </p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image">
<img alt="A rendering of Darwin Properties' senior living residence." class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="b1cf1b6e4fd500ee7c165a9c4ff5148c" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="1026a" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/a-rendering-of-darwin-properties-senior-living-residence.jpg?id=35231582&width=980"/>
<small class="image-media media-caption" placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">A rendering of Darwin Properties' senior living residence. </small><small class="image-media media-photo-credit" placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">(Darwin Properties)</small></p><p>One reason for the shortage is due to the timeline in building senior care. It’s been a six-year process, says Webbe. Their rezoning application was submitted in 2018 and the facility is expected to complete in early 2024. </p><p>Darwin, a long-time general contractor that began developing their own Northshore projects about a decade ago, partnered with Minto Properties on Lonsdale Square. The project includes a 113-unit rental building and 8,100 sq. ft of retail. The company does mostly rental housing and has also built a number of social housing units in Vancouver. </p><p>Webbe discovered that there is a “missing middle” for seniors with health issues, including dementia. He’s seeing others in his age group experience the same challenge.</p><p>And so, he’s stepped up, developing a privately funded seniors' assisted living and memory care facility in the City of North Vancouver, the first of many such projects for Darwin.</p><p>“Most of our focus is market rental housing, and we have decided that we are going to look at partnerships to basically increase the supply of memory care facilities on the Northshore,” he says. “We have probably over 65 acres of land in various stages of redevelopment and right away we decided to incorporate assisted living facilities into our projects.”</p><p>Darwin only invests in real estate on the Northshore even though the company does merchant development elsewhere.</p><p>“My hope is to share our story or our findings so that more people can understand what is going on with this market,” he says.</p><p>He found that there are about 40,000 people over 65 living on the Northshore, comprising more than 20% of the population.</p><p>Meanwhile, there are only 400 or so privately funded assisted living or memory care units, or one per 100 senior citizens living on the Northshore. When he needed to find a place for his in-laws, there was only the one unit available, at $15,000 per month. </p><p>“I think this market is probably a really good example of what other markets are experiencing, and my family has unfortunately experienced firsthand with my in-laws.</p><p>“Most of our friends are starting to experience this with their parents. With 40,000 seniors on the Northshore, we are starting to see this as a common conversation that my friends and I are having, due to health conditions, mental health and Alzheimer’s. </p><p>“Two of my friends had the exact same experience, and we are shocked with how expensive it is.”</p><p>His research team found that the current starting price of a seniors’ 325 sq. ft. one-bedroom unit is $10,000 per month, and that’s without any care. If any care is required, such as help with daily medications, the senior adds about $700 a month to that rent. If they have mobility issues and need help walking to the dining room, for example, they can add about $1,500 a month to that $10,000 a month rent, says Webbe.</p><p>And because there’s nothing available, they’d be lucky to find that.</p><p>Barbara J. Kirby is a former investment adviser who now works as a seniors' advocate in Vancouver, North Vancouver and Richmond. She helps people find housing and she also helps families across Canada navigate their way through the health care and housing systems when a loved elder needs help. </p><p>She gets around 10 calls a week and a lot of her work is listening to their stories and pointing seniors in the right direction. The biggest mistake they make is underestimating how much savings they’ll need for their senior years, which can easily cost $15,000 a month whether it’s for assisted living or 24-hour at-home care. </p><p>Sometimes, she helps people who are living in assisted living and their savings have run out.</p><p>“I get the call from the home saying, ‘We can’t keep her here, you have to help her,’” says Kirby. “We go through the health authority and if it’s urgent, she’s given the first available bed, or if we’re lucky, we can choose our top three choices… but sometimes those waiting lists for beds are one or two years.” </p><p>Kirby says that senior housing is in extremely short supply, especially facilities with memory care units. There are homes that are cutting out memory care entirely because of all the resources involved in maintaining such demanding care.</p><p>“Between North Vancouver and Vancouver those types of accommodations are sparse and very expensive,” she says of the type of housing that Webbe’s in-laws needed. “And if you want subsidized, it’s also very complicated, the waiting lists are long.” </p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 14:48:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/senior-housing-shortage-darwin-northshore/</guid><dc:creator>Kerry Gold</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/darwin-properties-under-construction-seniors-residence.jpg?id=35232440&amp;width=980"></media:content></item><item><title>Housing Market Resurgence Leads To Better Economic Growth In Some Provinces, But Slowdown Still To Come</title><link>https://storeys.com/desjardins-revised-economic-forecast-2023-2024/</link><description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34690708&width=1245&height=700&coordinates=0%2C31%2C0%2C31"/><br/><br/><p>Following an unexpectedly frenzied spring housing market, some provinces will be spared from the impending economic slowdown. At least, for now.</p><p>The "relative strength" of the rebound has led <a href="https://www.desjardins.com/content/dam/pdf/en/personal/savings-investment/economic-studies/provincial-outlook-july-25-2023.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Marc Desormeaux and Hélène Bégin, Principal Economists at Desjardins</a>, to alter their economic forecasts for some provinces and push the start of the downturn to 2024.</p><p>After the Bank of Canada (BoC) temporarily <a href="https://www.desjardins.com/content/dam/pdf/en/personal/savings-investment/economic-studies/provincial-outlook-july-25-2023.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">paused interest rate hikes</a>, most provinces experienced an <a href="https://storeys.com/canadian-home-sales-may-2023-crea/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_self">uptick in sales activity</a>. But in Ontario and British Columbia -- where affordability is already stretched -- the "robustness of gains...has been striking."</p><p>As such, the economic forecasts for the two housing-oriented provinces have been revised significantly higher, with Ontario and BC expected to see real GDP grow by 1.6% and 1.5%, respectively, in 2023.</p><p>Meanwhile, the less severe market downturn seen in Quebec over the last several years has been followed by a similarly less pronounced bounce back, leading Desormeaux and Bégin to believe the province will experience more modest real GDP growth of 0.4% this year.</p><p>Oil-producing regions, like Alberta and Saskatchewan, are still expected to fare the best, with the economists predicting annual real GDP growth of 2.9% and 2.8% for the provinces, respectively, in 2023.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image">
<img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="b97954bed44f96de44a818b1548e9d96" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="e7ea0" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34690682&width=980"/>
</p><p>All provinces have experienced economic expansion thus far in 2023 due to soaring population growth, but the source of newcomers will have an effect on the province's growth rankings.</p><p>Ontario and BC have welcomed a record number of non-permanent residents, but if the economy slows, then the number of temporary foreign workers admitted to Canada could fall. </p><p>In contrast, population growth in Alberta and the Maritimes has been driven not just by non-permanent residents, but by international immigration and interprovincial migration, too. Partly the result of the regions' affordable home prices, the growth is more likely to be sustained.</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image">
<img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="5a80d3728db5f1a8cb4d0bfdddd689df" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="21a40" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34690683&width=980"/>
</p><p>While the boisterous housing market and increased population growth have aided the economic outlook for 2023, they have not prevented a downturn, Desormeaux and Bégin warn. Rather, they have just delayed it until 2024.</p><p>"Monetary policy works with a lag, and all regions should increasingly feel the dampening impacts of sharply higher interest rates in the coming months," the economists said. </p><p>"As we approach 2024, more housing‐oriented provincial economies should see the more significant slowdowns we’ve long been expecting."</p><p class="shortcode-media shortcode-media-rebelmouse-image">
<img alt="" class="rm-shortcode" data-rm-shortcode-id="e154823d9353df168522531150e0c0e1" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" id="e9d2c" loading="lazy" src="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34690684&width=980"/>
</p><p>Cracks are already beginning to show, particularly in Ontario and BC. After the BoC <a href="https://storeys.com/bank-of-canada-raises-interest-rate-june/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_self">began hiking interest rates again in June</a>, the largest housing markets in both provinces -- <a href="https://storeys.com/gta-home-sales-average-price-june-2023/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_self">Toronto</a> and <a href="https://storeys.com/greater-vancouver-home-sales-prices-buyer-rebgv-statistics-june-2023/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_self">Vancouver</a> -- saw sales slow.</p><p>Desormeaux and Bégin expect the imminent economic slowdown to result in real GDP growth of 0.1% in Ontario, 0.2% in British Columbia, and 0.3% in Quebec in 2024. </p><p>Meanwhile, Newfoundland and Labrador will lead the economy on a national basis, with real GDP predicted to grow 1.1% in 2024. Alberta and Saskatchewan will follow, with real GDP expected to grow 1.0% and 0.9%, respectively, next year.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 22:05:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://storeys.com/desjardins-revised-economic-forecast-2023-2024/</guid><dc:creator>Zoe Demarco</dc:creator><media:content medium="image" type="image/jpeg" url="https://storeys.com/media-library/image.jpg?id=34690708&amp;width=980"></media:content></item></channel></rss>